<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<CodeLists name="CodeLists" date-last-modified="2015-06-23T16:42:28"  version="2.01"  xml:lang="en">
<Codelist name="AidType" xml:lang="en" category-codelist="AidType-category"  complete="1">
<metadata> <url>http://www.oecd.org/dac/stats/dacandcrscodelists.htm</url>
<name>"Aid Type"</name></metadata>
<codelist-items>   
<codelist-item><code>A01</code><category>A</category><name>General budget support</name><name xml:lang="fr">Soutien budgétaire général</name><description>Unearmarked contributions to the government budget including funding to support the implementation of macroeconomic reforms (structural adjustment programmes, poverty reduction strategies).Budget support is a method of financing a recipient country’s budget through a transfer of resources from an external financing agency to the recipient government’s national treasury. The funds thus transferred are managed in accordance with the recipient’s budgetary procedures. Funds transferred to the national treasury for financing programmes or projects managed according to different budgetary procedures from those of the recipient country, with the intention of earmarking the resources for specific uses, are therefore excluded.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Contributions au budget du gouvernement non préaffectées y compris le soutien à la mise en œuvre deréformes macroéconomiques (programmes d’ajustement structurel, stratégies de lutte contre lapauvreté). Le soutien budgétaire se définit comme une méthode de financement du budget d’un pays bénéficiaire via un transfert de ressources d’un organisme de financement externe au Trésor public du gouvernement bénéficiaire. Les fonds ainsi transférés sont gérés conformément aux procédures budgétaires du bénéficiaire. Cette définition n’englobe donc pas les fonds transférés au Trésor public pour le financement de programmes ou de projets gérés selon des procédures budgétaires différentes de celles du pays bénéficiaire, dans l’intention d’affecter ces ressources à des usages spécifiques.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>A02</code><category>A</category><name>Sector budget support</name><name xml:lang="fr">Soutien budgétaire sectoriel</name><description>Sector budget support, like general budget support, is a financial contribution to a recipient government’s budget.  However, in sector budget support, the dialogue between donors and partner governments focuses on sector-specific concerns, rather than on overall policy and budget priorities.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Le soutien budgétaire sectoriel, comme le soutien budgétaire général, est une contribution financière au budget du gouvernement du pays bénéficiaire. Cependant, dans le cas du soutien budgétaire sectoriel, le dialogue entre les donneurs et les gouvernements partenaires se concentre sur les préoccupations spécifiques à un secteur plutôt que sur les priorités de la politique globale et les priorités budgétaires.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>B01</code><category>B</category><name>Core support to NGOs, other private bodies, PPPs and research institutes</name><name xml:lang="fr">Contributions aux budgets réguliers des ONG, autres organismes privés, partenariats public-privé (PPP) et instituts de recherche</name><description>Funds are paid over to NGOs (local, national and international) for use at the latter’s discretion, and contribute to programmes and activities which NGOs have developed themselves, and which they implement on their own authority and responsibility. Core contributions to PPPs, funds paid over to foundations (e.g. philanthropic foundations), and contributions to research institutes (public and private) are also recorded here. Annex 2 of the DAC Directives provides a list of INGOs, PPPs and networks core contributions to which may be reported under B01. This list is not exclusive. </description><description xml:lang="fr">Fonds versés à des PPP, réseaux, instituts de recherche et organismes privés à but non lucratif – ONG basées dans des pays en développement, dans des pays donneurs ou ONG internationales et autres organisations de la société civile par exemple les fondations philanthropiques – qui sont utilisés à la discrétion de ces organisations, et qui contribuent au financement de programmes et activités que ces organisations ont mis au point elles-mêmes et qu’elles mettent en œuvre sous leur propre autorité et responsabilité.La Liste des organisations internationales éligible en APD (voir l’annexe 2) fournit une liste d’ONGI, de PPP et de réseaux en faveur desquels les contributions aux budgets réguliers peuvent être notifiées sous B01. Cette liste n’est pas exhaustive.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>B02</code><category>B</category><name>Core contributions to multilateral institutions</name><name xml:lang="fr">Contributions aux budgets réguliers des institutions multilatérales</name><description>These funds are classified as multilateral ODA (all other categories fall under bilateral ODA). The recipient multilateral institution pools contributions so that they lose their identity and become an integral part of its financial assets. See Annex 2 of the DAC Directives for a comprehensive list of agencies core contributions to which may be reported under B02 (Section I. Multilateral institutions).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Ces fonds sont comptabilisés en tant qu’APD multilatérale (toutes les autres catégories font partie de l’aide bilatérale). L’organisation internationale bénéficiaire fusionne les contributions, qui deviennent anonymes et font alors partie intégrante de ses avoirs financiers.La Liste des organisations internationales éligible en APD (voir l’annexe 2) fournit une liste complète des organisations en faveur desquelles les contributions aux budgets réguliers peuvent être notifiées sous B02.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>B03</code><category>B</category><name>Contributions to specific-purpose programmes and funds managed by international organisations (multilateral, INGO)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Contributions à des programmes ou fonds à objectif spécifique gérés par des organisations internationales (multilatérales, ONGI)</name><description>In addition to their core-funded operations, international organisations set up and raise funds for specific programmes and funds with clearly identified sectoral, thematic or geographical focus. Donors’ bilateral contributions to such programmes and funds are recorded here, e.g. “UNICEF girls’ education”, “Education For All Fast Track Initiative”, various trust funds, including for reconstruction (e.g. Afghanistan Reconstruction Trust Fund).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Outre leurs opérations de base, les organisations internationales mettent en place et lèvent des financements pour des programmes ou fonds qui visent des objectifs sectoriels, thématiques ou géographiques spécifiques. Les contributions des donneurs à ce type de programmes et fonds entrent dans cette catégorie, par exemple celles destinées au « Réseau pour l’éducation des femmes et des filles » parrainé par l’UNICEF, à l’« Initiative pour la mise en œuvre accélérée du programme d’éducation pour tous », ou à divers fonds d’affectation spéciale, y compris pour la reconstruction (par exemple le Fonds d’affectation spéciale pour la reconstruction de l’Afghanistan - ARTF).</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>B04</code><category>B</category><name>Basket funds/pooled funding</name><name xml:lang="fr">Fonds communs/financements groupés</name><description>The donor contributes funds to an autonomous account, managed jointly with other donors and/or the recipient. The account will have specific purposes, modes of disbursement and accountability mechanisms, and a limited time frame. Basket funds are characterised by common project documents, common funding contracts and common reporting/audit procedures with all donors. Donors’ contributions to funds managed autonomously by international organisations are recorded under B03.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Le donneur dépose des fonds sur un compte autonome, géré conjointement avec d’autres donneurs et/ou le bénéficiaire. Sont associés à ce compte des objectifs, des modalités de versement, des mécanismes de reddition de comptes spécifiques, et un horizon temporel précis.La mise en commun de fonds suppose des documents de projet communs, des contrats de financement communs et des procédures de notification/audit communes à tous les donneurs.Les contributions des donneurs à des fonds gérés par des organisations internationales sont notifiées sous B03.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>C01</code><category>C</category><name>Project-type interventions</name><name xml:lang="fr">Interventions de type projet</name><description>A project is a set of inputs, activities and outputs, agreed with the partner country*, to reach specific objectives/outcomes within a defined time frame, with a defined budget and a defined geographical area. Projects can vary significantly in terms of objectives, complexity, amounts involved and duration. There are smaller projects that might involve modest financial resources and last only a few months, whereas large projects might involve more significant amounts, entail successive phases and last for many years. A large project with a number of different components is sometimes referred to as a programme, but should nevertheless be recorded here.  Feasibility studies, appraisals and evaluations are included (whether designed as part of projects/programmes or dedicated funding arrangements).Aid channelled through NGOs or multilaterals is also recorded here. This includes payments for NGOs and multilaterals to implement donors’ projects and programmes, and funding of specified NGOs projects. By contrast, core funding of NGOs and multilaterals as well as contributions to specific-purpose funds managed by international organisations are recorded under B. * In the cases of equity investments, humanitarian aid or aid channelled through NGOs, projects are recorded here even if there was no direct agreement between the donor and the partner country.  </description><description xml:lang="fr">Un projet est un ensemble d’éléments, d’activités et de produits, convenus avec le pays partenaire*, en vue d’atteindre des objectifs/résultats spécifiques dans un laps de temps et une zone géographique prédéfinis au moyen d’un budget fixé à l’avance. Les projets peuvent différer considérablement par leurs objectifs, leur complexité, les montants en jeu et leur durée. Si les petits projets ne mettent en jeu que des ressources financières modestes et ne durent souvent que quelques mois, les grands projets peuvent porter sur des montants substantiels, devoir être mis en œuvre par tranches et durer plusieurs années. Lorsqu’un grand projet se subdivise en plusieurs composantes, il est parfois appelé programme, mais doit néanmoins être comptabilisé dans la présente rubrique.  Sont inclues les études de faisabilité, ainsi que les évaluations préalables ou  rétrospectives (qu’elles soient conçues comme un volet du projet/programme ou qu’elles fassent l’objet de modalités de financement dédiées).L’aide acheminée par l’intermédiaire d’ONG ou d’organisations multilatérales est également notifiée ici. Cela comprend les paiements effectués aux ONG et aux organisations multilatérales pour qu’elles mettent en œuvre les projets et programmes des donneurs, ainsi que le financement de projets spécifiques des ONG. En revanche, les contributions de caractère général aux ONG et aux organisations multilatérales ainsi que les contributions aux fonds à objectif spécifique gérés par des organisations internationales sont notifiées sous B. * Dans le cas d’investissements sous forme de prises de participation, d’une aide humanitaire ou d’une aide par l’intermédiaire d’ONG, les projets sont notifiés ici même s’ils ne font pas l’objet d’un accord direct avec le pays partenaire.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>D01</code><category>D</category><name>Donor country personnel</name><name xml:lang="fr">Personnel du pays donneur</name><description>Experts, consultants, teachers, academics, researchers, volunteers and contributions to public and private bodies for sending experts to developing countries.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Experts, consultants, enseignants, universitaires, chercheurs, stagiaires et volontaires, ainsi que contributions à des organismes publics et privés pour l’envoi d’experts dans les pays en développement. </description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>D02</code><category>D</category><name>Other technical assistance</name><name xml:lang="fr">Autres formes d’assistance technique </name><description>Provision, outside projects as described in category C01, of technical assistance in recipient countries (excluding technical assistance performed by donor experts reported under D01, and scholarships/training in donor country reported under E01). This includes training and research; language training; south-south studies; research studies; collaborative research between donor and recipient universities and organisations); local scholarships; development-oriented social and cultural programmes. This category also covers ad hoc contributions such as conferences, seminars and workshops, exchange visits, publications, etc.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Cette catégorie couvre l’apport de savoir-faire en dehors de projets tels qu’ils sont définis dans la catégorie C01 (sauf l’assistance technique fournie par des experts des pays donneurs couverte sous D01, et les bourses/formations dans le pays donneur couvertes sous E01.) Sont inclues les activités de formation et de recherche, les formations linguistiques, les études Sud-Sud, les études pour la recherche, les activités de recherche impliquant une collaboration entre des universités ou organismes du pays donneur et du pays bénéficiaire, les bourses locales, et les programmes sociaux et culturels à des fins de développement. La catégorie couvre également les contributions ponctuelles telles les conférences, séminaires et ateliers, échanges, publications, etc.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>E01</code><category>E</category><name>Scholarships/training in donor country</name><name xml:lang="fr">Bourses/formations dans le pays donneur</name><description>Financial aid awards for individual students and contributions to trainees.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Bourses octroyées à des étudiants et contributions aux frais associés à des stages.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>E02</code><category>E</category><name>Imputed student costs</name><name xml:lang="fr">Coûts imputés des étudiants</name><description>Indirect (“imputed”) costs of tuition in donor countries.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Coûts indirects (“imputés”) correspondant aux frais de scolarité dans le pays donneur.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>F01</code><category>F </category><name>Debt relief</name><name xml:lang="fr">Allégement de la dette</name><description>Groups all actions relating to debt (forgiveness, conversions, swaps, buy-backs, rescheduling, refinancing).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Regroupe toutes les actions se rapportant à la dette (annulation, conversion, échange, rachat, rééchelonnement, refinancement).</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>G01</code><category>G </category><name>Administrative costs not included elsewhere</name><name xml:lang="fr">Frais administratifs non inclus ailleurs</name><description>Administrative costs of development assistance programmes not already included under other ODA items as an integral part of the costs of delivering or implementing the aid provided. This category covers situation analyses and auditing activities.As regards the salaries component of administrative costs, it relates to  in-house agency staff and contractors only; costs associated with donor experts/consultants are to be reported under category C or D01.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Frais d'administration des programmes d'aide au développement qui ne sont pas déjà inclus dans d'autres rubriques comme partie intégrante du coût de l’acheminement ou de la mise en œuvre de l’aide fournie. Cette catégorie comprend les analyses de situation et les activités d’audit.En ce qui concerne la composante salariale des frais administratifs, elle se rapporte uniquement au personnel et contractuels de l’agence ; les coûts associés aux experts/consultants du pays donneur sont à notifier sous les catégories C ou D01.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>H01</code><category>H</category><name>Development awareness</name><name xml:lang="fr">Sensibilisation au développement </name><description>Funding of activities designed to increase public support, i.e. awareness in the donor country of development co-operation efforts, needs and issues.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Financement d’activités visant à accroître le soutien du public dans le pays donneur pour les efforts de coopération pour le développement et à rendre la population plus consciente des besoins et problèmes du développement.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>H02</code><category>H</category><name>Refugees in donor countries</name><name xml:lang="fr">Aide aux réfugiés dans le pays donneur</name><description>Official sector expenditures for the sustenance of refugees in donor countries during the first twelve months of their stay.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Dépenses allouées par le secteur public à l’entretien de réfugiés pendant les douze premiers mois de leur séjour dans le pays donneur.</description></codelist-item>
</codelist-items></Codelist>
<Codelist name="AidType-category" complete="1">
<metadata> <url>http://www.oecd.org/dac/stats/dacandcrscodelists.htm</url>
<name>"Aid Type (category)"</name></metadata>
<codelist-items>
<codelist-item><code>A</code><name>Budget support</name><name xml:lang="fr">Soutien budgétaire </name><description>Budget support</description><description xml:lang="fr">Soutien budgétaire </description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>B</code><name>Core contributions and pooled programmes and funds </name><name xml:lang="fr">Contributions aux budgets réguliers des organisations, programmes et financements groupés </name><description>Core contributions and pooled programmes and funds </description><description xml:lang="fr">Contributions aux budgets réguliers des organisations, programmes et financements groupés </description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>C</code><name>Project-type interventions</name><name xml:lang="fr">Interventions de type projet</name><description>Project-type interventions</description><description xml:lang="fr">Interventions de type projet</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>D</code><name>Experts and other technical assistance</name><name xml:lang="fr">Experts et autres formes d’assistance technique </name><description>Experts and other technical assistance</description><description xml:lang="fr">Experts et autres formes d’assistance technique </description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>E</code><name>Scholarships and student costs in donor countries</name><name xml:lang="fr">Bourses et autres frais d’étude dans les pays donneurs</name><description>Scholarships and student costs in donor countries</description><description xml:lang="fr">Bourses et autres frais d’étude dans les pays donneurs</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>F </code><name>Debt relief</name><name xml:lang="fr">Allégement de la dette</name><description>Debt relief</description><description xml:lang="fr">Allégement de la dette</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>G </code><name>Administrative costs not included elsewhere</name><name xml:lang="fr">Frais administratifs non inclus ailleurs</name><description>Administrative costs not included elsewhere</description><description xml:lang="fr">Frais administratifs non inclus ailleurs</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>H</code><name>Other in-donor expenditures</name><name xml:lang="fr">Autres dépenses dans le pays donneur</name><description>Other in-donor expenditures</description><description xml:lang="fr">Autres dépenses dans le pays donneur</description></codelist-item>
</codelist-items></Codelist>
<Codelist name="CollaborationType" complete="1">
<metadata> <url>http://www.oecd.org/dac/stats/dacandcrscodelists.htm</url>
<name>"Collaboration Type"</name></metadata>
<codelist-items>
<codelist-item><code>1</code><name>Bilateral</name><name xml:lang="fr">Bilateral</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>2</code><name>Multilateral (inflows)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Multilateral (inflows)</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>3</code><name>Bilateral, core contributions to NGOs and other private bodies / PPPs</name><name xml:lang="fr">Contributions bilatérales au budget général d'organisations non gouvernementales, d'autres organisations de la société civile, de partenariats publics-privés et d'instituts de recherches</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>4</code><name>Multilateral Outflows</name><name xml:lang="fr">Multilateral Outflows</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>6</code><name>Private Sector Outflows</name><name xml:lang="fr">Private Sector Outflows</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>7</code><name>Bilateral, ex-post NGO's</name><name xml:lang="fr">Bilateral, ex-post NGO's</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
</codelist-items></Codelist>
<Codelist name="FinanceType" xml:lang="en" category-codelist="FinanceType-category"  complete="1">
<metadata> <url>http://www.oecd.org/dac/stats/dacandcrscodelists.htm</url>
<name>"Finance Type"</name></metadata>
<codelist-items>
<codelist-item><code>1</code><category>0</category><name>GNI: Gross National Income</name><name xml:lang="fr">RNB : Revenu national brut</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>110</code><category>100</category><name>Aid grant excluding debt reorganisation</name><name xml:lang="fr">Don hors réorganisation de la dette (y compris quasi-dons)</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>111</code><category>100</category><name>Subsidies to national private investors</name><name xml:lang="fr">Don hors réorganisation de la dette (y compris quasi-dons)</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>210</code><category>200</category><name>Interest subsidy grant in AF </name><name xml:lang="fr">Bonification d’intérêt dans un financement mixte</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>211</code><category>200</category><name>Interest subsidy to national private exporters</name><name xml:lang="fr">Bonification d’intérêt octroyée aux exportateurs privés nationaux</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>310</code><category>300</category><name>Deposit basis</name><name xml:lang="fr">Base des dépôts</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>311</code><category>300</category><name>Encashment basis</name><name xml:lang="fr">Base des encaissements</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>410</code><category>400</category><name>Aid loan excluding debt reorganisation</name><name xml:lang="fr">Prêt d’aide hors réorganisation de la dette</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>411</code><category>400</category><name>Investment-related loan to developing countries</name><name xml:lang="fr">Prêt lié à un investissement dans les pays en développement</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>412</code><category>400</category><name>Loan in a joint venture with the recipient</name><name xml:lang="fr">Prêt dans une coentreprise avec le pays bénéficiaire</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>413</code><category>400</category><name>Loan to national private investor</name><name xml:lang="fr">Prêt à un investisseur privé national</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>414</code><category>400</category><name>Loan to national private exporter</name><name xml:lang="fr">Prêt à un exportateur privé national</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>451</code><category>450</category><name>Non-banks guaranteed export credits</name><name xml:lang="fr">Crédits à l'exportation garantis du secteur non bancaire</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>452</code><category>400</category><name>Non-banks non-guaranteed portions of guaranteed export credits</name><name xml:lang="fr">Fraction non garantie des crédits à l'exportation garantis du secteur bancaire</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>453</code><category>400</category><name>Bank export credits</name><name xml:lang="fr">Crédits à l'exportation du secteur bancaire</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>510</code><category>500</category><name>Acquisition of equity as part of a joint venture with the recipient</name><name xml:lang="fr">Acquisition de prises de participation dans une coentreprise avec le pays bénéficiaire</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>511</code><category>500</category><name>Acquisition of equity not part of joint venture in developing countries</name><name xml:lang="fr">Acquisition de prises de participation en dehors des coentreprises avec les pays en développement</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>512</code><category>500</category><name>Other acquisition of equity</name><name xml:lang="fr">Autre acquisition de prises de participation</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>610</code><category>600</category><name>Debt forgiveness:  ODA claims (P)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Annulation/conversion de la dette : créance APD (P)</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>611</code><category>600</category><name>Debt forgiveness: ODA claims (I)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Annulation/conversion de la dette : créance APD (I)</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>612</code><category>600</category><name>Debt forgiveness: OOF claims (P)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Annulation/conversion de la dette : créance AASP (P)</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>613</code><category>600</category><name>Debt forgiveness: OOF claims (I)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Annulation/conversion de la dette : créance AASP (I)</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>614</code><category>600</category><name>Debt forgiveness:  Private claims (P)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Annulation/conversion de la dette : créance du secteur privé (P)</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>615</code><category>600</category><name>Debt forgiveness:  Private claims (I)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Annulation/conversion de la dette : créance du secteur privé (I)</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>616</code><category>600</category><name>Debt forgiveness: OOF claims (DSR)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Annulation/conversion de la dette : créance AASP (DSR)</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>617</code><category>600</category><name>Debt forgiveness:  Private claims (DSR)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Annulation/conversion de la dette : créance du secteur privé (DSR)</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>618</code><category>600</category><name>Debt forgiveness: Other</name><name xml:lang="fr">Annulation/conversion de la dette : autre</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>620</code><category>600</category><name>Debt rescheduling: ODA claims (P)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Rééchelonnement de la dette : créance APD (P)</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>621</code><category>600</category><name>Debt rescheduling: ODA claims (I)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Rééchelonnement de la dette : créance APD (I)</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>622</code><category>600</category><name>Debt rescheduling: OOF claims (P)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Rééchelonnement de la dette : créance AASP (P)</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>623</code><category>600</category><name>Debt rescheduling: OOF claims (I)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Rééchelonnement de la dette : créance AASP (I)</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>624</code><category>600</category><name>Debt rescheduling:  Private claims (P)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Rééchelonnement de la dette : créance du secteur privé (P)</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>625</code><category>600</category><name>Debt rescheduling:  Private claims (I)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Rééchelonnement de la dette : créance du secteur privé (I)</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>626</code><category>600</category><name>Debt rescheduling: OOF claims (DSR)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Rééchelonnement de la dette : créance AASP (RSD)</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>627</code><category>600</category><name>Debt rescheduling:  Private claims (DSR)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Rééchelonnement de la dette : créance du secteur privé (RSD)</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>710</code><category>700</category><name>Foreign direct investment, new capital outflow (includes reinvested earnings if separate identification not available) </name><name xml:lang="fr">Investissement direct international</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>711</code><category>700</category><name>Other foreign direct investment, including reinvested earnings</name><name xml:lang="fr">Autre investissement direct international , y compris les bénéfices réinvestis</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>810</code><category>800</category><name>Bank bonds</name><name xml:lang="fr">Obligations du secteur bancaire</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>811</code><category>800</category><name>Non-bank  bonds</name><name xml:lang="fr">Obligations du secteur non bancaire</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>910</code><category>900</category><name>Other bank securities/claims</name><name xml:lang="fr">Autres titres/créances du secteur bancaire</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>911</code><category>900</category><name>Other non-bank securities/claims</name><name xml:lang="fr">Autres titres/créances du secteur non bancaire</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>912</code><category>900</category><name>Purchase of securities from issuing agencies</name><name xml:lang="fr">Titres et autres instruments émis par les agences multilatérales</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>2</code><category>0</category><name>ODA % GNI</name><name xml:lang="fr">APD en % du RNB</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>3</code><category>0</category><name>Total Flows % GNI</name><name xml:lang="fr">Apports totaux en % du RNB</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>4</code><category>0</category><name>Population</name><name xml:lang="fr">Population</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>630</code><category>600</category><name>Debt rescheduling: OOF claim (DSR – original loan principal) </name><name xml:lang="fr">Rééchelonnement de la dette : créance AASP (RSD – principal du prêt d’origine)</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>631</code><category>600</category><name>Debt rescheduling: OOF claim (DSR – original loan interest)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Rééchelonnement de la dette : créance AASP (RSD – intérêts du prêt d’origine)</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>632</code><category>600</category><name>Debt rescheduling: Private claim (DSR – original loan principal)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Rééchelonnement de la dette : créance du secteur privé (RSD – principal du prêt d’origine)</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
</codelist-items></Codelist>
<Codelist name="FinanceType-category" complete="1">
<metadata> <url>http://www.oecd.org/dac/stats/dacandcrscodelists.htm</url>
<name>"Finance Type (category)"</name></metadata>
<codelist-items>
<codelist-item><code>0</code><name>NON FLOW ITEMS</name><name xml:lang="fr">AUTRE QU’APPORTS </name><description>Non resource flow items requested on DAC table 1</description><description xml:lang="fr">Rubriques requises sur le tableau CAD 1 portant sur des informations autre que des apports</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>100</code><name>GRANT</name><name xml:lang="fr">DON</name><description>Transfers in cash or in kind for which no legal debt is incurred by the recipient.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Transferts en espèces ou en nature qui n'entraînent pas d'obligation juridique de remboursement pour le bénéficiaire.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>200</code><name>INTEREST SUBSIDY</name><name xml:lang="fr">BONIFICATION  D’INTERET</name><description>Subsidies to soften the terms of private export credits, or loans or credits by the banking sector.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Subventions visant à assouplir les conditions des crédits à l’exportation ou des prêts/crédits du secteur bancaire.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>300</code><name>CAPITAL SUBSCRIPTION</name><name xml:lang="fr">SOUSCRIPTION AU CAPITAL</name><description>Payments to multilateral agencies in the form of notes and similar instruments, unconditionally cashable at sight by the recipient institutions.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Versements aux agences multilatérales sous forme de billets à ordre et effets similaires encaissables à vue sans condition par l'institution bénéficiaire.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>400</code><name>LOAN</name><name xml:lang="fr">PRÊT</name><description>Transfers in cash or in kind for which the recipient incurs legal debt.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Transferts en espèce ou en nature qui entraînent une obligation juridique de remboursement pour le bénéficiaire.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>500</code><name>EQUITY</name><name xml:lang="fr">PRISES DE PARTICIPATION</name><description>Investment in a country on the DAC List of ODA Recipients that is not made to acquire a lasting interest in an enterprise.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Attestent de la propriété d’une société et confèrent un droit au propriétaire sur la valeur résiduelle de la société une fois que les créances des créditeurs ont été honorées.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>600</code><name>DEBT RELIEF</name><name xml:lang="fr">ALLEGEMENT DE LA DETTE</name><description>Debt cancellations, debt conversions, debt rescheduling within or outside the framework of the Paris Club.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Annulation de dette, conversion de dette, rééchelonnement de dette au sein ou en dehors du Club de Paris.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>700</code><name>INVESTMENT</name><name xml:lang="fr">INVESTISSEMENTS DIRECTS INTERNATIONAUX</name><description>Investment made by a private entity resident in a reporting country to acquire or add to a lasting interest(1) in an enterprise in a country on the DAC List of ODA Recipients.  </description><description xml:lang="fr">L’investissement direct est motivé par la volonté d’une entité résidente d’un pays déclarant d’acquérir ou de maintenir un intérêt durable1 dans une entité résidente d’un pays en développement.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>800</code><name>BONDS</name><name xml:lang="fr">OBLIGATIONS</name><description>Acquisition of bonds issued by developing countries.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Acquisition d’obligations émises par les pays en développement.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>900</code><name>OTHER SECURITIES/CLAIMS</name><name xml:lang="fr">AUTRES TITRES/CREANCES</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
</codelist-items></Codelist>
<Codelist name="FlowType" complete="1">
<metadata> <url>http://www.oecd.org/dac/stats/dacandcrscodelists.htm</url>
<name>"Flow Type"</name></metadata>
<codelist-items>
<codelist-item><code>10</code><name>ODA</name><name xml:lang="fr">APD</name><description>Official Development Assistance</description><description xml:lang="fr">Aide Publique au Développement</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>20</code><name>OOF</name><name xml:lang="fr">AASP</name><description>Other Official Flows</description><description xml:lang="fr">Autres Apports du Secteur Public</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>30</code><name>Private grants</name><name xml:lang="fr">Apports privés</name><description>Grants made by NGOs and other civil society organisations (e.g. philantropic foundations) based in the reporting DAC country.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Dons fournis par les ONG et autres organismes privés (par exemple fondations philantropiques) résidents dans le pays donneur</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>35</code><name>Private Market</name><name xml:lang="fr">Apports privés aux conditions du marché</name><description>Private long-term (i.e. over one-year maturity) capital transactions made by residents of DAC countries.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Apports privés aux conditions du marché</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>40</code><name>Non Flows</name><name xml:lang="fr">non apports</name><description>GNI, ODA%GNI, Population etc</description><description xml:lang="fr">RNB, APD%RNB, Population etc</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>50</code><name>Other Flows</name><name xml:lang="fr">Autres apports</name><description>e.g. non-ODA component of peacebuilding operations</description><description xml:lang="fr">ex : élément non APD des opérations de maintien de la paix</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31</code><name>Multilateral Private Flows</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
</codelist-items></Codelist>
<Codelist name="Sector" xml:lang="en" category-codelist="SectorCategory"  complete="1">
<metadata> <url>http://www.oecd.org/dac/stats/dacandcrscodelists.htm</url>
<name>"DAC 5 Digit Sector"</name></metadata>
<codelist-items>
<codelist-item><code>32164</code><category>321</category><name>Chemicals</name><name xml:lang="fr">Produits chimiques</name><description>Industrial and non-industrial production facilities; includes pesticides production.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Production industrielle et non industrielle ; y compris fabrication des pesticides.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32165</code><category>321</category><name>Fertilizer plants</name><name xml:lang="fr">Production d’engrais chimiques</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32166</code><category>321</category><name>Cement/lime/plaster</name><name xml:lang="fr">Ciment, chaux et plâtre</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32167</code><category>321</category><name>Energy manufacturing</name><name xml:lang="fr">Fabrication d’énergie</name><description>Including gas liquefaction; petroleum refineries.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris liquéfaction du gaz ; raffineries de pétrole.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>15111</code><category>151</category><name>Public finance management</name><name xml:lang="fr">Gestion des finances publiques</name><description>Fiscal policy and planning; support to ministries of finance; strengthening financial and managerial accountability; public expenditure management; improving financial management systems; tax policy and administration; budget drafting; inter-governmental fiscal relations, public audit, public debt. (Use code 15114 for revenue-generating tax support and code 33120 for customs).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Politique et planification budgétaires ; soutien aux ministères des finances ; renforcement de la responsabilité financière et administrative ; gestion des dépenses publiques ; amélioration des systèmes de gestion financière ; politique et administration fiscales ; préparation du budget ; relations budgétaires intergouvernementales, audit public, dette publique. (Utiliser les codes 15114 pour le soutien à la collecte de l impôt et 33120 pour les douanes.)</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>11110</code><category>111</category><name>Education policy &amp; admin. management</name><name xml:lang="fr">Politique de l’éducation et gestion administrative</name><description>Education sector policy, planning and programmes; aid to education ministries, administration and management systems; institution capacity building and advice; school management and governance; curriculum and materials development; unspecified education activities.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Politique de l’éducation, planification et programmes ; aide aux ministères de l’éducation, à l’administration et au développement de systèmes de gestion, renforcement des capacités institutionnelles et conseils ; gestion et direction des écoles, développement des programmes d’études et des matériels pédagogiques ; activités d’éducation non spécifiées.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>11120</code><category>111</category><name>Education facilities and training</name><name xml:lang="fr">Equipements scolaires et formation</name><description>Educational buildings, equipment, materials; subsidiary services to education (boarding facilities, staff housing); language training; colloquia, seminars, lectures, etc.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Bâtiments scolaires, équipement, fournitures ; services pour l’éducation (équipement pour les pensionnaires, logement pour le personnel) ; cours de langues ; colloques, séminaires, conférences, etc.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>11130</code><category>111</category><name>Teacher training</name><name xml:lang="fr">Formation des enseignants</name><description>Teacher education (where the level of education is unspecified); in-service and pre-service training; materials development.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Éducation des enseignants (quand le niveau d’éducation n’est pas spécifié) ; formation et formation continue ; développement des matériels pédagogiques.  </description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>11182</code><category>111</category><name>Educational research</name><name xml:lang="fr">Recherche en éducation</name><description>Research and studies on education effectiveness, relevance and quality; systematic evaluation and monitoring.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Recherche et études sur l’efficacité, la pertinence et la qualité de l’éducation ; évaluation et suivi systématiques. </description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>11220</code><category>112</category><name>Primary education</name><name xml:lang="fr">Enseignement primaire</name><description>Formal and non-formal primary education for children; all elementary and first cycle systematic instruction; provision of learning materials.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Enseignement primaire formel et non formel pour les enfants ; enseignement élémentaire général ; fournitures scolaires.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>11230</code><category>112</category><name>Basic life skills for youth &amp; adults</name><name xml:lang="fr">Education pour une meilleure qualité de vie pour les jeunes et les adultes</name><description>Formal and non-formal education for basic life skills for young people and adults (adults education); literacy and numeracy training.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Éducation formelle et non formelle pour une meilleure qualité de vie pour les jeunes et les adultes (éducation des adultes) ; alphabétisation et apprentissage du calcul.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>11240</code><category>112</category><name>Early childhood education</name><name xml:lang="fr">Education de la petite enfance</name><description>Formal and non-formal pre-school education.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Éducation préscolaire formelle et non formelle.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>11320</code><category>113</category><name>Secondary education</name><name xml:lang="fr">Enseignement secondaire</name><description>Second cycle systematic instruction at both junior and senior levels.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Éducation secondaire généralisée pour les premiers et derniers cycles.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>11330</code><category>113</category><name>Vocational training</name><name xml:lang="fr">Formation professionnelle</name><description>Elementary vocational training and secondary level technical education; on-the job training; apprenticeships; including informal vocational training.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Formation professionnelle élémentaire et enseignement technique au niveau secondaire ; formation sur le tas ; apprentissage.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>11420</code><category>114</category><name>Higher education</name><name xml:lang="fr">Enseignement supérieur</name><description>Degree and diploma programmes at universities, colleges and polytechnics; scholarships.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Diplômes universitaires, de l’enseignement supérieur, de technologie ; bourses d’études.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>11430</code><category>114</category><name>Advanced tech. &amp; managerial training</name><name xml:lang="fr">Formation technique supérieure de gestion</name><description>Professional-level vocational training programmes and in-service training.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Formation professionnelle supérieure et formation sur le tas.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>12110</code><category>121</category><name>Health policy &amp; admin. management</name><name xml:lang="fr">Politique de la santé et gestion administrative</name><description>Health sector policy, planning and programmes; aid to health ministries, public health administration; institution capacity building and advice; medical insurance programmes; unspecified health activities.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Politique de la santé, planification et programmes ; aide aux ministères de la santé ; administration de la santé publique ; renforcement des capacités institutionnelles et conseils ; programmes d’assurance-maladie ; activités de santé non spécifiés.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>12181</code><category>121</category><name>Medical education/training</name><name xml:lang="fr">Education et formation médicales</name><description>Medical education and training for tertiary level services.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Enseignement médical et formation pour les services au niveau tertiaire.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>12182</code><category>121</category><name>Medical research</name><name xml:lang="fr">Recherche médicale</name><description>General medical research (excluding basic health research).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Recherche médicale (à l’exclusion de la recherche sur la santé de base).</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>12191</code><category>121</category><name>Medical services</name><name xml:lang="fr">Services médicaux</name><description>Laboratories, specialised clinics and hospitals (including equipment and supplies); ambulances; dental services; mental health care; medical rehabilitation; control of non-infectious diseases; drug and substance abuse control [excluding narcotics traffic control (16063)].</description><description xml:lang="fr">Laboratoires, centres de santé et hôpitaux spécialisés (y compris l’équipement et les fournitures) ; ambulances ; services dentaires ; santé mentale ; rééducation médicale ; lutte contre les maladies à l’exclusion des maladies infectieuses ; lutte contre la toxicomanie [à l’exclusion du trafic de drogues (16063)].</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>12220</code><category>122</category><name>Basic health care</name><name xml:lang="fr">Soins et services de santé de base</name><description>Basic and primary health care programmes; paramedical and nursing care programmes; supply of drugs, medicines and vaccines related to basic health care.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Programmes de soins sanitaires primaires et de base ; programmes de soins paramédicaux et infirmiers ; approvisionnement en médicaments et en vaccins relatifs aux soins et services de santé de base.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>12230</code><category>122</category><name>Basic health infrastructure</name><name xml:lang="fr">Infrastructure pour la santé de base</name><description>District-level hospitals, clinics and dispensaries and related medical equipment; excluding specialised hospitals and clinics (12191).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Hôpitaux régionaux, centres de santé, dispensaires et équipements médicaux ; à l’exclusion des hôpitaux et centres de santé spécialisés (12191).</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>12240</code><category>122</category><name>Basic nutrition</name><name xml:lang="fr">Nutrition de base</name><description>Direct feeding programmes (maternal feeding, breastfeeding and weaning foods, child feeding, school feeding); determination of micro-nutrient deficiencies; provision of vitamin A, iodine, iron etc.; monitoring of nutritional status; nutrition and food hygiene education; household food security.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Programmes pour l’alimentation (alimentation maternelle, allaitement et alimentation du sevrage, alimentation de l’enfant, alimentation à l’école) ; identification des déficiences nutritives ; fourniture de vitamine A, d’iode, de fer, etc. ; surveillance de l’état nutritionnel ; enseignement de la nutrition et de l’hygiène alimentaire ; alimentation domestique.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>12250</code><category>122</category><name>Infectious disease control</name><name xml:lang="fr">Lutte contre les maladies infectieuses</name><description>Immunisation; prevention and control of infectious and parasite diseases, except malaria (12262), tuberculosis (12263), HIV/AIDS and other STDs (13040). It includes diarrheal diseases, vector-borne diseases (e.g. river blindness and guinea worm), viral diseases, mycosis, helminthiasis, zoonosis, diseases by other bacteria and viruses, pediculosis, etc.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Vaccination ;  prévention et lutte contre les maladies infectieuses parasitaires à l’exception du paludisme (12262), de la tuberculose (12263), du VIH/sida et autres MST (13040). Ceci inclus les diarrhées chroniques, les maladies transmises par un vecteur (par exemple onchocercose, bilharziose), les maladies virales, les mycoses, l’helminthiasis, les zoonoses et les maladies provoquées par d’autres bactéries et virus, pédiculose, etc. </description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>12261</code><category>122</category><name>Health education</name><name xml:lang="fr">Education sanitaire</name><description>Information, education and training of the population for improving health knowledge and practices; public health and awareness campaigns; promotion of improved personal hygiene practices, including use of sanitation facilities and handwashing with soap.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Information, éducation et formation de la population pour l’amélioration des connaissances et des pratiques liées à la santé ; campagnes pour la santé publique et programmes de sensibilisation ; promotion de meilleures pratiques d’hygiène personnelle, notamment de l’utilisation d’équipements sanitaires et du savonnage des mains.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>12262</code><category>122</category><name>Malaria control</name><name xml:lang="fr">Lutte contre le paludisme</name><description>Prevention and control of malaria.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Prévention et lutte contre le paludisme.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>12263</code><category>122</category><name>Tuberculosis control</name><name xml:lang="fr">Lutte contre la tuberculose</name><description>Immunisation, prevention and control of tuberculosis.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Vaccination, prévention et lutte contre la tuberculose.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>15151</code><category>151</category><name>Elections</name><name xml:lang="fr">Elections</name><description>Electoral management bodies and processes, election observation, voters' education. (Use code 15230 when in the context of an international peacekeeping operation.)</description><description xml:lang="fr">Organes et processus de gestion électorale, observation des processus électoraux, éducation civique des électeurs. (Utiliser le code 15230 lorsque les activités se déroulent dans le cadre d'une opération internationale de maintien de la paix.)</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>15160</code><category>151</category><name>Human rights</name><name xml:lang="fr">Droits de la personne</name><description>Measures to support specialised official human rights institutions and mechanisms at universal, regional, national and local levels in their statutory roles to promote and protect civil and political, economic, social and cultural rights as defined in international conventions and covenants; translation of international human rights commitments into national legislation; reporting and follow-up; human rights dialogue. Human rights defenders and human rights NGOs; human rights advocacy, activism, mobilisation; awareness raising and public human rights education. Human rights programming targeting specific groups, e.g. children, persons with disabilities, migrants, ethnic, religious, linguistic and sexual minorities, indigenous people and those suffering from caste discrimination, victims of trafficking, victims of torture. (Use code 15230 when in the context of a peacekeeping operation)</description><description xml:lang="fr">Mesures visant à soutenir les institutions et mécanismes spécialisés dans les droits de la personne opérant aux niveaux mondial, régional, national ou local, dans leur mission officielle de promotion et de protection des droits civils et politiques, économiques, sociaux et culturels tels qu’ils sont définis dans les conventions et pactes internationaux ; transposition dans la législation nationale des engagements internationaux concernant les droits de la personne ; notification et suivi ; dialo</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>15153</code><category>151</category><name>Media and free flow of information</name><name xml:lang="fr">Médias et liberté de l'information</name><description>Activities that support free and uncensored flow of information on public issues; activities that increase the editorial and technical skills and the integrity of the print and broadcast media, e.g. training of journalists. (Use codes 22010-22040 for provision of equipment and capital assistance to media.)</description><description xml:lang="fr">Activités qui favorisent une diffusion libre et non censurée de l’information sur les questions publiques ; activités visant à améliorer les compétences rédactionnelles et techniques, et l’intégrité des médias – presse écrite, radio et télévision – par exemple, formation des journalistes. (Utiliser les codes 22010?22040 pour la fourniture d’équipements et d’une aide financière aux médias.)</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>14021</code><category>140</category><name>Water supply - large systems</name><name xml:lang="fr">Approvisionnement en eau – systèmes à grande échelle</name><description>Potable water treatment plants; intake works; storage; water supply pumping stations; large scale transmission / conveyance and distribution systems.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Usines de traitement d’eau potable ; ouvrages d’adduction ; stockage ; stations de pompage pour l’approvisionnement en eau ; réseaux d’adduction et de distribution à grande échelle. </description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>14022</code><category>140</category><name>Sanitation - large systems</name><name xml:lang="fr">Assainissement – systèmes à grande échelle</name><description>Large scale sewerage including trunk sewers and sewage pumping stations; domestic and industrial waste water treatment plants.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Réseaux d’assainissement à grande échelle y compris égouts et stations de pompage des eaux d’égouts ; usines de traitement des eaux usées domestiques et industrielles.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>14031</code><category>140</category><name>Basic drinking water supply</name><name xml:lang="fr">Approvisionnement en eau potable – dispositifs de base</name><description>Rural water supply schemes using handpumps, spring catchments, gravity-fed systems, rainwater collection and fog harvesting, storage tanks, small distribution systems typically with shared connections/points of use. Urban schemes using handpumps and local neighbourhood networks including those with shared connections.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Dispositifs ruraux d’approvisionnement en eau reposant sur des pompes manuelles, des captages de sources, des systèmes par gravité, la collecte des eaux de pluie et de brouillard, des citernes, des systèmes simplifiés de distribution avec points d’eau collectifs/branchements partagés. Dispositifs urbains utilisant des pompes manuelles et mini-réseaux, y compris ceux avec branchements partagés et bornes-fontaines. </description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32168</code><category>321</category><name>Pharmaceutical production</name><name xml:lang="fr">Produits pharmaceutiques</name><description>Medical equipment/supplies; drugs, medicines, vaccines; hygienic products.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Matériel médical et fournitures médicales ; médicaments et vaccins ; produits d’hygiène corporelle.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32169</code><category>321</category><name>Basic metal industries</name><name xml:lang="fr">Industrie métallurgique de base</name><description>Iron and steel, structural metal production.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Sidérurgie, éléments de construction métallique.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>14032</code><category>140</category><name>Basic sanitation</name><name xml:lang="fr">Assainissement – dispositifs de base</name><description>Latrines, on-site disposal and alternative sanitation systems, including the promotion of household and community investments in the construction of these facilities. (Use code 12261 for activities promoting improved personal hygiene practices.)</description><description xml:lang="fr">Latrines, dispositifs d’assainissement autonomes et systèmes alternatifs, y compris la promotion d’investissements de la part des ménages et des communautés locales dans la construction d’équipements de ce type. (Utiliser le code 12261 pour les activités de promotion des règles d’hygiène personnelle.)</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>12281</code><category>122</category><name>Health personnel development</name><name xml:lang="fr">Formation de personnel de santé</name><description>Training of health staff for basic health care services.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Formation du personnel de santé pour les services et les soins sanitaires de base.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>13010</code><category>130</category><name>Population policy and admin. mgmt</name><name xml:lang="fr">Politique/programmes en matière de population et gestion administrative</name><description>Population/development policies; census work, vital registration; migration data; demographic research/analysis; reproductive health research; unspecified population activities.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Politique en matière de population et de développement ; recensement, enregistrement des naissances/décès ; données sur la migration ; recherche et analyse démographiques ; recherche en santé et fertilité ; activités de population non spécifiées.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>13020</code><category>130</category><name>Reproductive health care</name><name xml:lang="fr">Soins en matière de fertilité</name><description>Promotion of reproductive health; prenatal and postnatal care including delivery; prevention and treatment of infertility; prevention and management of consequences of abortion; safe motherhood activities.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Santé et fertilité ; soins prénatals et périnatals, y compris l’accouchement ; prévention et traitement de la stérilité ; prévention et suites de l’avortement ; activités pour une maternité sans risque.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>13030</code><category>130</category><name>Family planning</name><name xml:lang="fr">Planification familiale</name><description>Family planning services including counselling; information, education and communication (IEC) activities; delivery of contraceptives; capacity building and training.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Conseils en planification familiale ; activités d’information, d’éducation et de communication (IEC) ; distribution de produits contraceptifs ; accroissement des moyens et aptitudes, formation.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>13040</code><category>130</category><name>Std control including hiv/aids</name><name xml:lang="fr">Lutte contre les MST et VIH/sida</name><description>All activities related to sexually transmitted diseases and HIV/AIDS control e.g. information, education and communication; testing; prevention; treatment, care.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Toutes activités liées au contrôle des maladies sexuellement transmissibles et du VIH/sida ; activités d’information, éducation et communication ; dépistage ; prévention ; traitement, soins.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>13081</code><category>130</category><name>Personnel dvpt: pop. &amp; repro health</name><name xml:lang="fr">Formation de personnel en matière de population et de santé et fertilité</name><description>Education and training of health staff for population and reproductive health care services.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Éducation et formation du personnel de santé pour les services de population ainsi que les soins en matière de santé et fertilité.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>14010</code><category>140</category><name>Water resources policy/admin. mgmt</name><name xml:lang="fr">Politique des ressources en eau et gestion administrative</name><description>Water sector policy and governance, including legislation, regulation, planning and management as well as transboundary management of water; institutional capacity development; activities supporting the Integrated Water Resource Management approach (IWRM:  see box below).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Politique et gouvernance du secteur de l’eau, y compris législation, réglementation, planification et gestion ainsi que gestion transfrontalière de l’eau; renforcement des capacités institutionnelles ; activités favorisant une approche intégrée de la gestion des ressources en eau (GIRE).</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>14015</code><category>140</category><name>Water resources protection</name><name xml:lang="fr">Protection des ressources en eau</name><description>Collection and usage of quantitative and qualitative data on water resources; creation and sharing of water knowledge; conservation and rehabilitation of inland surface waters (rivers, lakes etc.), ground water and coastal waters; prevention of water contamination.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Collecte et utilisation de données quantitatives et qualitatives sur les ressources en eau ; création et mise en commun de connaissances sur l’eau ; préservation et remise en état des eaux intérieures de surface (rivières, lacs, etc.), des nappes souterraines et des eaux côtières ; prévention de la contamination des eaux.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>14020</code><category>140</category><name>Water supply &amp; sanit. - large systems</name><name xml:lang="fr">Approvisionnement en eau et assainissement - systèmes à grande échelle</name><description>Programmes where components according to 14021 and 14022 cannot be identified.  When components are known, they should individually be reported under their respective purpose codes:  water supply [14021], sanitation [14022], and hygiene [12261].</description><description xml:lang="fr">Programmes dont les composantes relatives aux codes 14021 et 14022 ne peuvent être identifiées séparément. Lorsque les composantes sont connues, elles devraient être individuellement notifiées sous leurs codes respectifs : approvisionnement en eau [14021], assainissement [14022] et hygiène [12261].</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>14030</code><category>140</category><name>Basic drinking water supply and basic sanitation</name><name xml:lang="fr">Approvisionnement en eau potable et assainissement - dispositifs de base</name><description>Programmes where components according to 14031 and 14032 cannot be identified.  When components are known, they should individually be reported under their respective purpose codes:  water supply [14031], sanitation [14032], and hygiene [12261].</description><description xml:lang="fr">Programmes dont les composantes relatives aux codes 14031 et 14032 ne peuvent être identifiées séparément. Lorsque les composantes sont connues, elles devraient être individuellement notifiées sous leurs codes respectifs : approvisionnement en eau [14031], assainissement [14032] et hygiène [12261].</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>14040</code><category>140</category><name>River basins development</name><name xml:lang="fr">Aménagement de bassins fluviaux</name><description>Infrastructure-focused integrated river basin projects and related institutional activities; river flow control; dams and reservoirs [excluding dams primarily for irrigation (31140) and hydropower (23065) and activities related to river transport (21040)].</description><description xml:lang="fr">Projets de bassins fluviaux centrés sur les infrastructures et activités institutionnelles connexes ; régulation des cours d’eau ; barrages et réservoirs [à l’exclusion des barrages hydroélectriques (23065) et barrages pour l’irrigation (31140) et activités liées au transport fluvial (21040)]. </description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>14050</code><category>140</category><name>Waste management/disposal</name><name xml:lang="fr">Traitement des déchets</name><description>Municipal and industrial solid waste management, including hazardous and toxic waste; collection, disposal and treatment; landfill areas; composting and reuse.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Au niveau municipal et industriel, y compris les déchets dangereux et toxiques ; enlèvement et traitement ; zones d’enfouissement des déchets ; compost et recyclage.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>14081</code><category>140</category><name>Educ./trng:water supply &amp; sanitation</name><name xml:lang="fr">Education/formation dans la distribution d'eau et l'assainissement</name><description>Education and training for sector professionals and service providers.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Activités d’éducation et de formation destinées aux professionnels et fournisseurs de services de ce secteur.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>15110</code><category>151</category><name>Public sector policy and adm. management</name><name xml:lang="fr">Politiques publiques et gestion administrative</name><description>Institution-building assistance to strengthen core public sector management systems and capacities. This includes macro-economic and other policy management, co-ordination, planning and reform; human resource management; organisational development; civil service reform; e-government; development planning, monitoring and evaluation; support to ministries involved in aid co-ordination; other ministries and government departments when sector cannot be specified. (Use specific sector codes for development of systems and capacities in sector ministries.)</description><description xml:lang="fr">Aide au renforcement des institutions visant à consolider les capacités et systèmes principaux de gestion du secteur public. Ceci recouvre la gestion macroéconomique et la gestion d’autres politiques, la coordination, la planification et la réforme ; la gestion des ressources humaines ; le développement organisationnel ; la réforme de la fonction publique ; l’administration électronique ; la planification, le suivi et l’évaluation du développement ; le soutien aux ministères participant à la coo</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>15130</code><category>151</category><name>Legal and judicial development</name><name xml:lang="fr">Développement des services légaux et judiciaires</name><description>Support to institutions, systems and procedures of the justice sector, both formal and informal; support to ministries of justice, the interior and home affairs; judges and courts; legal drafting services; bar and lawyers associations; professional legal education; maintenance of law and order and public safety; border management; law enforcement agencies, police, prisons and their supervision; ombudsmen; alternative dispute resolution, arbitration and mediation; legal aid and counsel; traditional, indigenous and paralegal practices that fall outside the formal legal system. Measures that support the improvement of legal frameworks, constitutions, laws and regulations; legislative and constitutional drafting and review; legal reform; integration of formal and informal systems of law. Public legal education; dissemination of information on entitlements and remedies for injustice; awareness campaigns. (Use codes 152xx for activities that are primarily aimed at supporting security system reform or undertaken in connection with post-conflict and peace building activities.)</description><description xml:lang="fr">Soutien aux institutions, systèmes et procédures du secteur de la justice, aussi bien officiels que non officiels ; soutien aux ministères de la justice et de l’intérieur ; juges et tribunaux ; services de rédaction des actes juridiques ; associations d’avocats et de juristes ; formation juridique professionnelle ; maintien de l’ordre et de la sécurité publique ; gestion des frontières ; organismes chargés de faire respecter la loi, police, prisons et leur supervision ; médiateurs ; mécanismes a</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>15150</code><category>151</category><name>Democratic participation and civil society</name><name xml:lang="fr">Participation démocratique et société civile</name><description>Support to the exercise of democracy and diverse forms of participation of citizens beyond elections (15151); direct democracy instruments such as referenda and citizens’ initiatives; support to organisations to represent and advocate for their members, to monitor, engage and hold governments to account, and to help citizens learn to act in the public sphere; curricula and teaching for civic education at various levels. (This purpose code is restricted to activities targeting governance issues. When assistance to civil society is for non-governance purposes use other appropriate purpose codes.)</description><description xml:lang="fr">Soutien à l’exercice de la démocratie et à diverses formes de participation des citoyens, excepté les élections (15151) ; instruments de démocratie directe comme les référendums et les initiatives de citoyens ; soutien aux organisations pour représenter et défendre leurs membres, assurer un suivi, participer et demander des comptes aux gouvernements, et pour aider les citoyens à apprendre à agir dans la sphère publique ; programmes d’études et enseignement de l’éducation civique à différents niv</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>15210</code><category>152</category><name>Security system management and reform</name><name xml:lang="fr">Gestion et réforme des systèmes de sécurité</name><description>Technical co-operation provided to parliament, government ministries, law enforcement agencies and the judiciary to assist review and reform of the security system to improve democratic governance and civilian control; technical co-operation provided to government to improve civilian oversight and democratic control of budgeting, management, accountability and auditing of security expenditure, including military budgets, as part of a public expenditure management programme; assistance to civil society to enhance its competence and capacity to scrutinise the security system so that it is managed in accordance with democratic norms and principles of accountability, transparency and good governance. [Other than in the context of an international peacekeeping operation (15230)].</description><description xml:lang="fr">Coopération technique en faveur des parlements, des ministères publics, des services chargés de faire respecter la loi et des instances judiciaires pour aider à examiner et à réformer les systèmes de sécurité afin d’améliorer la gouvernance démocratique et le contrôle par les civils ; coopération technique en faveur des gouvernements à l’appui du renforcement de la supervision civile et du contrôle démocratique sur la budgétisation, la gestion, la transparence et l’audit des dépenses de sécurit</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>15220</code><category>152</category><name>Civilian peace-building, conflict prevention and resolution</name><name xml:lang="fr">Dispositifs civils de construction de la paix, préventioni et règlement</name><description>Support for civilian activities related to peace building, conflict prevention and resolution, including capacity building, monitoring, dialogue and information exchange. Bilateral participation in international civilian peace missions such as those conducted by the UN Department of Political Affairs (UNDPA) or the European Union (European Security and Defence Policy), and contributions to civilian peace funds or commissions (e.g. Peacebuilding Commission, Peacebuilding thematic window of the MDG achievement fund etc.). The contributions can take the form of financing or provision of equipment or civilian or military personnel (e.g. for training civilians).(Use code 15230 for bilateral participation in international peacekeeping operations).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Aide à des activités civiles de construction de la paix, et de prévention et de règlement des conflits, y compris renforcement des capacités, suivi, dialogue et échange d’informations. Participation bilatérale à des missions civiles internationales en faveur de la paix comme celles qui sont conduites par le Département des affaires politiques des Nations unies (UNDPA) ou l'Union européenne (Politique européenne de sécurité et de défense), et contributions à des fonds ou commissions civils pour l</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31110</code><category>311</category><name>Agricultural policy &amp; admin. mgmt</name><name xml:lang="fr">Politique agricole et gestion administrative</name><description>Agricultural sector policy, planning and programmes; aid to agricultural ministries;  institution capacity building and advice; unspecified agriculture.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Politique agricole, planification et programmes ; aide aux ministères de l’agriculture ; renforcement des capacités institutionnelles et conseils ; activités d’agriculture non spécifiées.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31120</code><category>311</category><name>Agricultural development</name><name xml:lang="fr">Développement agricole</name><description>Integrated projects; farm development.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Projets intégrés ; développement d’exploitations agricoles.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31130</code><category>311</category><name>Agricultural land resources</name><name xml:lang="fr">Ressources en terres cultivables</name><description>Including soil degradation control; soil improvement; drainage of water logged areas; soil desalination; agricultural land surveys; land reclamation; erosion control, desertification control.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris la lutte contre la dégradation des sols ; amélioration des sols ; drainage des zones inondées ; dessalage des sols ; études des terrains agricoles ; remise en état des sols ; lutte contre l’érosion, lutte contre la désertification.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31140</code><category>311</category><name>Agricultural water resources</name><name xml:lang="fr">Ressources en eau à usage agricole</name><description>Irrigation, reservoirs, hydraulic structures, ground water exploitation for agricultural use.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Irrigation, réservoirs, structures hydrauliques, exploitation de nappes phréatiques. </description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31150</code><category>311</category><name>Agricultural inputs</name><name xml:lang="fr">Produits à usage agricole</name><description>Supply of seeds, fertilizers, agricultural machinery/equipment.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Approvisionnement en semences, engrais, matériel et outillage agricoles.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31161</code><category>311</category><name>Food crop production</name><name xml:lang="fr">Production agricole</name><description>Including grains (wheat, rice, barley, maize, rye, oats, millet, sorghum); horticulture; vegetables; fruit and berries; other annual and perennial crops. [Use code 32161 for agro-industries.]</description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris céréales (froment, riz, orge, maïs, seigle, avoine, millet, sorgho) ; horticulture ; légumes ; fruits et baies ; autres cultures annuelles et pluriannuelles. [Utiliser le code 32161 pour les agro-industries.]</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>15230</code><category>152</category><name>Participation in international peacekeeping operations</name><name xml:lang="fr">Maintien de la paix à l’issue d’un conflit (NU)</name><description>Bilateral participation in peacekeeping operations mandated or authorised by the United Nations (UN) through Security Council resolutions, and conducted by international organisations, e.g. UN, NATO, the European Union (Security and Defence Policy security-related operations), or regional groupings of developing countries. Direct contributions to the UN Department for Peacekeeping Operations (UNDPKO) budget are excluded from bilateral ODA (they are reportable in part as multilateral ODA, see Annex 9). The activities that can be reported as bilateral ODA under this code are limited to: human rights and election monitoring; reintegration of demobilised soldiers; rehabilitation of basic national infrastructure; monitoring or retraining of civil administrators and police forces; security sector reform and other rule of law-related activities; training in customs and border control procedures; advice or training in fiscal or macroeconomic stabilisation policy; repatriation and demobilisation of armed factions, and disposal of their weapons; explosive mine removal. The enforcement aspects of international peacekeeping operations are not reportable as ODA. ODA-eligible bilateral participation in peacekeeping operations can take the form of financing or provision of equipment or military or civilian personnel (e.g. police officers). The reportable cost is calculated as the excess over what the personnel and equipment would have cost to maintain had they not been assigned to take part in a peace operation. Costs for military contingents participating in UNDPKO peacekeeping operations are not reportable as ODA. International peacekeeping operations may include humanitarian-type activities (contributions to the form of equipment or personnel), as described in codes 7xxxx. These should be included under code 15230 if they are an integrated part of the activities above, otherwise they should be reported as humanitarian aid. NB: When using this code, indicate the name of the operation in the short description of the activity reported.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Participation bilatérale à des opérations de maintien de la paix mandatées ou autorisées par les Nations unies (NU) à travers des résolutions du Conseil de sécurité, et conduites par des organisations internationales, par exemple les Nations unies, l’OTAN, l’Union européenne (opérations liées à la sécurité dans le cadre de la Politique européenne de sécurité et de défense) ou des groupements régionaux de pays en développement.Les contributions directes au budget du Département des opérations de</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>15240</code><category>152</category><name>Reintegration and SALW control</name><name xml:lang="fr">Réintégration et contrôle des armes légères et de petit calibre</name><description>Reintegration of demobilised military personnel into the economy; conversion of production facilities from military to civilian outputs; technical co-operation to control, prevent and/or reduce the proliferation of small arms and light weapons (SALW) – see para. 80 of the Directives for definition of SALW activities covered. [Other than in the context of an international peacekeeping operation (15230) or child soldiers (15261)].</description><description xml:lang="fr">Réinsertion du personnel militaire démobilisé dans la vie économique et civile ; conversion des usines d’armes en usines de produits à usage civil ; coopération technique destinée à contrôler, prévenir et/ou réduire la prolifération d’armes légères et de petit calibre – voir le paragraphe 80 des Directives pour la définition des activités couvertes. [Autre que dans le cadre d’une opération internationale de maintien de la paix (15230) ou  enfants soldats (15261)].</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>15250</code><category>152</category><name>Removal of land mines and explosive remnants of war</name><name xml:lang="fr">Enlèvement des minse terrestres</name><description>All activities related to land mines and explosive remnants of war which have benefits to developing countries as their main objective, including removal of land mines and explosive remnants of war, and stockpile destruction for developmental purposes [other than in the context of an international peacekeeping operation (15230)]; risk education and awareness raising; rehabilitation, reintegration and assistance to victims, and research and development on demining and clearance. Only activities for civilian purposes are ODA-eligible.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Toutes les activités liées aux mines terrestres et aux restes explosifs de guerre dont le but essentiel est de bénéficier aux pays en développement, y compris l'enlèvement des mines terrestres et des restes explosifs de guerre et la destruction des stocks à des fins de développement [autre qu'en rapport avec la participation à des opérations internationales de maintien de la paix (15230)] ; sensibilisation au risque ; réhabilitation, réinsertion et assistance aux victimes, et les activités de re</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>15261</code><category>152</category><name>Child soldiers (prevention and demobilisation)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Enfants soldats (Prévention et démobilisation)</name><description>Technical co-operation provided to government – and assistance to civil society organisations – to support and apply legislation designed to prevent the recruitment of child soldiers, and to demobilise, disarm, reintegrate, repatriate and resettle (DDR) child soldiers.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Coopération technique en faveur des gouvernements – et assistance aux organisations de la société civile – à l’appui de l’adoption et de l’application de lois destinées à empêcher le recrutement d’enfants en tant que soldats ; appui à la démobilisation, au désarmement, à la réinsertion, au rapatriement et à la réintégration (DDR) des enfants soldats. </description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32170</code><category>321</category><name>Non-ferrous metal industries</name><name xml:lang="fr">Industries des métaux non ferreux</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32171</code><category>321</category><name>Engineering</name><name xml:lang="fr">Construction mécanique et électrique</name><description>Manufacturing of electrical and non-electrical machinery, engines/turbines.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Fabrication de machines électriques et non électriques, moteurs et turbines.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>16010</code><category>160</category><name>Social/welfare services</name><name xml:lang="fr">Services sociaux</name><description>Social legislation and administration; institution capacity building and advice; social security and other social schemes; special programmes for the elderly, orphans, the disabled, street children; social dimensions of structural adjustment; unspecified social infrastructure and services, including consumer protection.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Législation et administration sociales ; renforcement des capacités institutionnelles et conseils ; sécurité sociale et autres plans sociaux ; programmes spécifiques pour les personnes âgées, orphelins, handicapés, enfants abandonnés ; dimensions sociales de l’ajustement structurel ; infrastructure et services sociaux non spécifiés, y compris la protection des consommateurs.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>16020</code><category>160</category><name>Employment policy and admin. mgmt.</name><name xml:lang="fr">Politique de l’emploi et gestion administrative</name><description>Employment policy and planning; labour law; labour unions; institution capacity building and advice; support programmes for unemployed; employment creation and income generation programmes; occupational safety and health; combating child labour.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Politique et planification de l’emploi ; législation ; syndicats ; renforcement des capacités institutionnelles et conseils ; programmes de l’aide aux chômeurs ; programmes de création d’emplois et de génération de revenus ; sécurité et santé dans le travail ; lutte contre le travail des enfants.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>16030</code><category>160</category><name>Housing policy and admin. management</name><name xml:lang="fr">Politique du logement et gestion administrative</name><description>Housing sector policy, planning and programmes;  excluding low-cost housing and slum clearance (16040).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Politique du logement, planification et programmes ; à l’exclusion du logement à coût réduit (16040).</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>16040</code><category>160</category><name>Low-cost housing</name><name xml:lang="fr">Logement à coût réduit</name><description>Including slum clearance.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris la suppression des bidonvilles.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>16050</code><category>160</category><name>Multisector aid for basic soc. serv.</name><name xml:lang="fr">Aide plurisectorielle pour les services sociaux de base</name><description>Basic social services are defined to include basic education, basic health, basic nutrition, population/reproductive health and basic drinking water supply and basic sanitation.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Les services sociaux de base incluent l’éducation de base, la santé de base, les activités en matière de population/santé et fertilité ainsi que les systèmes de distribution d’eau potable de base et assainissement de base.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>16061</code><category>160</category><name>Culture and recreation</name><name xml:lang="fr">Culture et loisirs</name><description>Including libraries and museums.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris bibliothèques et musées.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>16062</code><category>160</category><name>Statistical capacity building</name><name xml:lang="fr">Renforcement des capacités statistiques</name><description>Both in national statistical offices and any other government ministries.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Dans les offices statistiques nationaux et les autres ministères concernés.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>16063</code><category>160</category><name>Narcotics control</name><name xml:lang="fr">Lutte contre le trafic de drogues</name><description>In-country and customs controls including training of the police; educational programmes and awareness campaigns to restrict narcotics traffic and in-country distribution.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Contrôles intérieurs et contrôles douaniers y compris la formation de la police, programmes d’éducation et de sensibilisation pour limiter le trafic de drogues et la distribution domestique1.La comptabilisation dans l’APD des dépenses liées à la lutte contre le trafic de drogues est limitée aux activités qui se focalisent sur le développement économique et l’amélioration du niveau de vie, y compris les programmes de développement alternatifs et la substitution des plantations. Les activités fi</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>16064</code><category>160</category><name>Social mitigation of HIV/AIDS</name><name xml:lang="fr">ATTENUATION DE L'IMPACT SOCIAL DU VIH/SIDA</name><description>Special programmes to address the consequences of HIV/AIDS, e.g. social, legal and economic assistance to people living with HIV/AIDS including food security and employment; support to vulnerable groups and children orphaned by HIV/AIDS; human rights of HIV/AIDS affected people. </description><description xml:lang="fr">Programmes spéciaux visant les conséquences sociales du VIH/sida, par exemple assistance sociale, juridique et économique aux personnes vivant avec le VIH/sida y compris sécurité alimentaire et emploi ; soutien aux groupes vulnérables et aux enfants orphelins du sida ; droits de l’homme pour les personnes atteintes par le VIH/sida.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>15170</code><category>151</category><name>Women's equality organisations and institutions</name><name xml:lang="fr">Organisations et institutions pour l’égalité des femmes</name><description>Support for institutions and organisations (governmental and non-governmental) working for gender equality and women’s empowerment.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Soutien aux institutions et organisations (gouvernementales et non gouvernementales) qui œuvrent pour l’égalité homme?femme et l’autonomisation des femmes.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>15112</code><category>151</category><name>Decentralisation and support to subnational govt.</name><name xml:lang="fr">Décentralisation et soutien aux administrations infranationales</name><description>Decentralisation processes (including political, administrative and fiscal dimensions); intergovernmental relations and federalism; strengthening departments of regional and local government, regional and local authorities and their national associations. (Use specific sector codes for decentralisation of sector management and services.) </description><description xml:lang="fr">Processus de décentralisation (y compris aspects politiques, administratifs et budgétaires) ; relations intergouvernementales et fédéralisme ; renforcement des services des administrations régionales et locales, des autorités régionales et locales et de leurs associations nationales. (Utiliser des codes sectoriels spécifiques pour la décentralisation de la gestion et des services sectoriels.)</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>15113</code><category>151</category><name>Anti-corruption organisations and institutions</name><name xml:lang="fr">organisations et institutions pour la lutte contre la corruption</name><description>Specialised organisations, institutions and frameworks for the prevention of and combat against corruption, bribery, money-laundering and other aspects of organised crime, with or without law enforcement powers, e.g. anti-corruption commissions and monitoring bodies, special investigation services, institutions and initiatives of integrity and ethics oversight, specialised NGOs, other civil society and citizens’ organisations directly concerned with corruption.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Organisations, institutions et cadres spécialisés dans la prévention et la lutte contre la corruption active et passive, le blanchiment d’argent et d’autres aspects du crime organisé, dotés ou non de pouvoirs pour faire respecter la loi, comme les commissions chargées de la lutte contre la corruption et les organismes de suivi, les services spéciaux d’enquête, les institutions et les initiatives de contrôle de l’intégrité et de l’éthique, les ONG spécialisées, d’autres organisations de citoyens </description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>91010</code><category>910</category><name>Administrative costs (non-sector allocable)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Frais administratifs</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>93010</code><category>930</category><name>Refugees in donor countries (non-sector allocable)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Réfugiés dans le pays donneur</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>99810</code><category>998</category><name>Sectors not specified</name><name xml:lang="fr">Secteur non spécifié</name><description>Contributions to general development of the recipient should be included under programme assistance (51010).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Les contributions au développement général du pays bénéficiaire devraient être incluses dans l’aide programme (51010).</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>15152</code><category>151</category><name>Legislatures and political parties</name><name xml:lang="fr">Assemblées législatives et parties politiques</name><description>Assistance to strengthen key functions of legislatures/ parliaments including subnational assemblies and councils (representation; oversight; legislation), such as improving the capacity of legislative bodies, improving legislatures’ committees and administrative procedures,; research and information management systems; providing training programmes for legislators and support personnel. Assistance to political parties and strengthening of party systems.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Aide au renforcement des fonctions clés des assemblées législatives/parlements, y compris des assemblées et conseils infranationaux (représentation ; surveillance ; législation), par exemple amélioration des capacités des organes législatifs, amélioration du fonctionnement des commissions et des procédures administratives des assemblées législatives ; systèmes de gestion de la recherche et de l’information ; mise en place de programmes de formation à l’intention des législateurs et du personnel </description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>21010</code><category>210</category><name>Transport policy &amp; admin. management</name><name xml:lang="fr">Politique des transports et gestion administrative</name><description>Transport sector policy, planning and programmes; aid to transport ministries; institution capacity building and advice; unspecified transport; activities that combine road, rail, water and/or air transport.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Politique des transports, planification et programmes ; aide aux ministères du transport ; renforcement des capacités institutionnelles et conseils ; transports non spécifiés ; activités qui recouvrent le transport routier, le transport ferroviaire, le transport par voies d’eau et/ou le transport aérien.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>21020</code><category>210</category><name>Road transport</name><name xml:lang="fr">Transport routier</name><description>Road infrastructure, road vehicles; passenger road transport, motor passenger cars.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Infrastructure routière, véhicules ; transport routier de voyageurs, voitures particulières.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>21030</code><category>210</category><name>Rail transport</name><name xml:lang="fr">Transport ferroviaire</name><description>Rail infrastructure, rail equipment, locomotives, other rolling stock; including light rail (tram) and underground systems.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Infrastructure ferroviaire, matériel ferroviaire, locomotives, autre matériel roulant ; y compris les tramways et les métropolitains.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>21040</code><category>210</category><name>Water transport</name><name xml:lang="fr">Transport par voies d’eau</name><description>Harbours and docks, harbour guidance systems, ships and boats; river and other inland water transport, inland barges and vessels.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Ports et docks, systèmes de guidage, navires et bateaux ; transport sur voies navigables intérieures, bateaux de voies d’eau intérieures.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>21050</code><category>210</category><name>Air transport</name><name xml:lang="fr">Transport aérien</name><description>Airports, airport guidance systems, aeroplanes, aeroplane maintenance equipment.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Aéroports, systèmes de guidage, avions, équipement d’entretien des avions.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>21061</code><category>210</category><name>Storage</name><name xml:lang="fr">Stockage</name><description>Whether or not related to transportation.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Associé ou non au transport.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>21081</code><category>210</category><name>Educ./trng in transport &amp; storage</name><name xml:lang="fr">Education/formation dans les transports et le stockage</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>22010</code><category>220</category><name>Communications policy &amp; admin. mgmt</name><name xml:lang="fr">Politique des communications et gestion administrative</name><description>Communications sector policy, planning and programmes; institution capacity building and advice; including postal services development; unspecified communications activities.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Politique des communications, planification et programmes ; renforcement des capacités institutionnelles et conseils ; y compris développement des services postaux ; activités de communications non spécifiées.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>22020</code><category>220</category><name>Telecommunications</name><name xml:lang="fr">Télécommunications</name><description>Telephone networks, telecommunication satellites, earth stations.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Réseaux de téléphones, satellites, stations terrestres.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>22030</code><category>220</category><name>Radio/television/print media</name><name xml:lang="fr">Radio, télévision, presse écrite</name><description>Radio and TV links, equipment; newspapers; printing and publishing.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Liaisons et équipement ; journaux ; imprimerie et édition.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>22040</code><category>220</category><name>Information and communication technology (ICT)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Technologies de l'information et de la communication</name><description>Computer hardware and software; internet access; IT training.  When sector cannot be specified.  </description><description xml:lang="fr">Matériel informatique et logiciels ; accès Internet ; formations aux TI. Lorsque le secteur ne peut pas être spécifié.  </description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>23010</code><category>230</category><name>Energy policy and admin. management</name><name xml:lang="fr">Politique de l’énergie et gestion administrative</name><description>Energy sector policy, planning and programmes; aid to energy ministries; institution capacity building and advice; unspecified energy activities including energy conservation.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Politique de l’énergie, planification et programmes ; aide aux ministères de l’énergie ; renforcement des capacités institutionnelles et conseils ; activités non spécifiées dans le domaine de l’énergie y compris les économies d’énergie.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>23020</code><category>230</category><name>Power generat./non-renewable sources</name><name xml:lang="fr">Production d’énergie (sources non renouvelables)</name><description>Thermal power plants including when heat source cannot be determined; combined gas-coal power plants.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Centrales thermiques (lorsque la source de chaleur ne peut être déterminée) ; centrales alimentées au gaz et au charbon.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>23030</code><category>230</category><name>Power generation/renewable sources</name><name xml:lang="fr">Production d’énergie (sources renouvelables)</name><description>Including policy, planning, development programmes, surveys and incentives. Fuelwood/ charcoal production should be included under forestry (31261).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris politique et planification, programmes de développement, études et primes. Production de bois de chauffage et de charbon de bois devrait être incluse dans sylviculture (31261).</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>23040</code><category>230</category><name>Electrical transmission/distribution</name><name xml:lang="fr">Transmission et distribution d’électricité</name><description>Distribution from power source to end user; transmission lines.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Distribution de la source d’énergie au consommateur ; lignes de transmission.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>23050</code><category>230</category><name>Gas distribution</name><name xml:lang="fr">Distribution de gaz</name><description>Delivery for use by ultimate consumer.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Distribution au consommateur. </description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>23061</code><category>230</category><name>Oil-fired power plants</name><name xml:lang="fr">Centrales alimentées au fuel</name><description>Including diesel power plants.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris les centrales alimentées au gas-oil.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>23062</code><category>230</category><name>Gas-fired power plants</name><name xml:lang="fr">Centrales alimentées au gaz</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>23063</code><category>230</category><name>Coal-fired power plants</name><name xml:lang="fr">Centrales alimentées au charbon</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>23064</code><category>230</category><name>Nuclear power plants</name><name xml:lang="fr">Centrales nucléaires</name><description>Including nuclear safety. Assistance towards the peaceful use of nuclear energy is reportable as ODA. This includes the construction and decommissioning of nuclear power reactors for civilian power supply, the development or supply of medical isotopes, and food irradiation and other industrial and commercial applications. Nuclear weapons research and other military applications of nuclear technology are excluded.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris la sécurité nucléaire.L’aide visant à favoriser une utilisation pacifique de l’énergie nucléaire est comptabilisable dans l’APD. À titre d’exemples, on citera : la construction ou le déclassement de centrales nucléaires à des fins civiles, le développement ou la fourniture d’isotopes médicaux, l’irradiation des aliments et d’autres applications industrielles et commerciales. Sont par contre exclues les activités de recherche sur les armes nucléaires et les applications militaires de l</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>23065</code><category>230</category><name>Hydro-electric power plants</name><name xml:lang="fr">Centrales et barrages hydroélectriques</name><description>Including power-generating river barges.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris les installations sur les barges.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>23066</code><category>230</category><name>Geothermal energy</name><name xml:lang="fr">Energie géothermique</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>23067</code><category>230</category><name>Solar energy</name><name xml:lang="fr">Energie solaire</name><description>Including photo-voltaic cells, solar thermal applications and solar heating.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris les cellules photovoltaïques et les pompes à énergie solaire.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>23068</code><category>230</category><name>Wind power</name><name xml:lang="fr">Energie éolienne</name><description>Wind energy for water lifting and electric power generation.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Énergie éolienne pour l’hydrodynamique et la production d’électricité.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>23069</code><category>230</category><name>Ocean power</name><name xml:lang="fr">Energie marémotrice</name><description>Including ocean thermal energy conversion, tidal and wave power.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris la conversion de l’énergie thermique marine, la puissance des marées et des vagues.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>23070</code><category>230</category><name>Biomass</name><name xml:lang="fr">Biomasse</name><description>Densification technologies and use of biomass for direct power generation including biogas, gas obtained from sugar cane and other plant residues, anaerobic digesters.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Technologies de densification et utilisation de la biomasse pour la production d’énergie directe, y compris le gaz obtenu par fermentation de la canne à sucre et d’autres résidus végétaux, et par anaérobie.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>23081</code><category>230</category><name>Energy education/training</name><name xml:lang="fr">Education et formation dans le domaine de l’énergie</name><description>Applies to all energy sub-sectors; all levels of training.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Se rapporte à tous les sous-secteurs de l’énergie et à tous les niveaux de formation.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>23082</code><category>230</category><name>Energy research</name><name xml:lang="fr">Recherche dans le domaine de l'énergie</name><description>Including general inventories, surveys.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris inventaires et études.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>24010</code><category>240</category><name>Financial policy &amp; admin. management</name><name xml:lang="fr">Politique des finances et gestion administrative</name><description>Finance sector policy, planning and programmes; institution capacity building and advice; financial markets and systems.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Politique des finances, planification et  programmes ; renforcement des capacités institutionnelles et conseils ; marchés et systèmes financiers.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>24020</code><category>240</category><name>Monetary institutions</name><name xml:lang="fr">Institutions monétaires</name><description>Central banks.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Banques centrales.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>24030</code><category>240</category><name>Formal sector financ. intermediaries</name><name xml:lang="fr">Intermédiaires financiers officiels</name><description>All formal sector financial intermediaries; credit lines; insurance, leasing, venture capital, etc. (except when focused on only one sector).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Tous les intermédiaires financiers dans le secteur formel ; lignes de crédit ; assurance, crédit-bail, capital-risque, etc. (sauf ceux spécialisés dans un seul secteur).</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>24040</code><category>240</category><name>Informal/semi-formal fin. intermed.</name><name xml:lang="fr">Intermédiaires financiers du secteur informel et semi-formel</name><description>Micro credit, savings and credit co-operatives etc.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Micro crédits, coopératives d’épargne et de crédit, etc.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>24081</code><category>240</category><name>Education/trng in banking &amp; fin. services</name><name xml:lang="fr">Formation dans la banque et les services financiers</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>25010</code><category>250</category><name>Business support services &amp; institutions</name><name xml:lang="fr">Services et institutions de soutien commerciaux</name><description>Support to trade and business associations, chambers of commerce; legal and regulatory reform aimed at improving business and investment climate; private sector institution capacity building and advice; trade information; public-private sector networking including trade fairs; e-commerce.  Where sector cannot be specified: general support to private sector enterprises (in particular, use code 32130 for enterprises in the industrial sector).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Soutien aux associations de commerce et d’entreprises, chambres de commerce ; réformes juridiques et réglementaires afin d’améliorer les activités liées à l’entreprise ; renforcement des capacités institutionnelles du secteur privé et conseils ; information commerciale ; réseaux de liaison entre les secteurs public et privé y compris les foires commerciales ; commerce électronique. Quand le secteur ne peut pas être spécifié : soutien général aux entreprises du secteur privé. En particulier, pour</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>25020</code><category>250</category><name>Privatisation</name><name xml:lang="fr">Privatisation</name><description>When sector cannot be specified.  Including general state enterprise restructuring or demonopolisation programmes; planning, programming, advice.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Lorsque le secteur ne peut être spécifié. Y compris programmes de restructuration d’entreprises publiques et de démonopolisation ; planification, programmation, conseils.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31162</code><category>311</category><name>Industrial crops/export crops</name><name xml:lang="fr">Récoltes destinées à l’exportation</name><description>Including sugar; coffee, cocoa, tea; oil seeds, nuts, kernels; fibre crops; tobacco; rubber.  [Use code 32161 for agro-industries.]</description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris sucre ; café, cacao, thé ; oléagineux, graines, noix, amandes ; fibres ; tabac ; caoutchouc. [Utiliser le  code 32161 pour les agro-industries.]</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31163</code><category>311</category><name>Livestock</name><name xml:lang="fr">Bétail</name><description>Animal husbandry; animal feed aid.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Toutes formes d’élevage ; aliments pour animaux.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31164</code><category>311</category><name>Agrarian reform</name><name xml:lang="fr">Réforme agraire</name><description>Including agricultural sector adjustment.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris ajustement structurel dans le secteur agricole.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31165</code><category>311</category><name>Agricultural alternative development</name><name xml:lang="fr">Développement agricole alternatif</name><description>Projects to reduce illicit drug cultivation through other agricultural marketing and production opportunities (see code 43050 for non-agricultural alternative development).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Projets afin de réduire les cultures illicites (drogue) à travers d’autres opportunités de marketing et production agricoles (voir code 43050 pour développement alternatif non agricole).</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31166</code><category>311</category><name>Agricultural extension</name><name xml:lang="fr">Vulgarisation agricole</name><description>Non-formal training in agriculture.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Formation agricole non formelle.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31181</code><category>311</category><name>Agricultural education/training</name><name xml:lang="fr">Education et formation dans le domaine agricole</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31182</code><category>311</category><name>Agricultural research</name><name xml:lang="fr">Recherche agricole</name><description>Plant breeding, physiology, genetic resources, ecology, taxonomy, disease control, agricultural bio-technology; including livestock research (animal health, breeding and genetics, nutrition, physiology).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Étude des espèces végétales, physiologie, ressources génétiques, écologie, taxonomie, lutte contre les maladies, biotechnologie agricole ; y compris recherche vétérinaire (dans les domaines génétiques et sanitaires, nutrition, physiologie).</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31191</code><category>311</category><name>Agricultural services</name><name xml:lang="fr">Services agricoles</name><description>Marketing policies &amp; organisation; storage and transportation, creation of strategic reserves.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Organisation et politiques des marchés ; transport et stockage ; établissements de réserves stratégiques.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31192</code><category>311</category><name>Plant and post-harvest protection and pest control</name><name xml:lang="fr">Protection des plantes et des récoltes, lutte antiacridienne</name><description>Including integrated plant protection, biological plant protection activities, supply and management of agrochemicals, supply of pesticides, plant protection policy and legislation.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris la protection intégrée des plantes, les activités de protection biologique des plantes, la fourniture et la gestion de substances agrochimiques, l’approvisionnement en pesticides ; politique et législation de la protection des plantes.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31193</code><category>311</category><name>Agricultural financial services</name><name xml:lang="fr">Services financiers agricoles</name><description>Financial intermediaries for the agricultural sector including credit schemes; crop insurance.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Intermédiaires financiers du secteur agricole, y compris les plans de crédit ; assurance récoltes.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31194</code><category>311</category><name>Agricultural co-operatives</name><name xml:lang="fr">Coopératives agricoles</name><description>Including farmers’ organisations.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris les organisations d’agriculteurs. </description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31195</code><category>311</category><name>Livestock/veterinary services</name><name xml:lang="fr">Services vétérinaires (bétail)</name><description>Animal health and management, genetic resources, feed resources.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Santé des animaux, ressources génétiques et nutritives.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31210</code><category>312</category><name>Forestry policy &amp; admin. management</name><name xml:lang="fr">Politique de la sylviculture et gestion administrative</name><description>Forestry sector policy, planning and programmes; institution capacity building and advice; forest surveys; unspecified forestry and agro-forestry activities.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Politique de la sylviculture, planification et programmes ; renforcement des capacités institutionnelles et conseils ; études des forêts ; activités sylvicoles et agricoles liées à la sylviculture non spécifiées.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31220</code><category>312</category><name>Forestry development</name><name xml:lang="fr">Développement sylvicole</name><description>Afforestation for industrial and rural consumption; exploitation and utilisation; erosion control, desertification control; integrated forestry projects.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Boisement pour consommation rurale et industrielle ; exploitation et utilisation ; lutte contre l’érosion, lutte contre la désertification ; projets intégrés.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31261</code><category>312</category><name>Fuelwood/charcoal</name><name xml:lang="fr">Reboisement (bois et charbon de bois)</name><description>Forestry development whose primary purpose is production of fuelwood and charcoal.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Développement sylvicole visant à la production de bois de chauffage et de charbon de bois. </description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31281</code><category>312</category><name>Forestry education/training</name><name xml:lang="fr">Education et formation en sylviculture</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31282</code><category>312</category><name>Forestry research</name><name xml:lang="fr">Recherche en sylviculture</name><description>Including artificial regeneration, genetic improvement, production methods, fertilizer, harvesting.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris reproduction artificielle et amélioration des espèces, méthodes de production, engrais, coupe et ramassage du bois.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31291</code><category>312</category><name>Forestry services</name><name xml:lang="fr">Services sylvicoles</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31310</code><category>313</category><name>Fishing policy and admin. management</name><name xml:lang="fr">Politique de la pêche et gestion administrative</name><description>Fishing sector policy, planning and programmes; institution capacity building and advice; ocean and coastal fishing; marine and freshwater fish surveys and prospecting; fishing boats/equipment; unspecified fishing activities.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Politique de la pêche, planification et programmes ; renforcement des capacités institutionnelles et conseils ; pêche hauturière et côtière ; évaluation, études et prospection du poisson en milieu marin et fluvial ; bateaux et équipements de pêche ; activités de pêche non spécifiées.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31320</code><category>313</category><name>Fishery development</name><name xml:lang="fr">Développement de la pêche</name><description>Exploitation and utilisation of fisheries; fish stock protection; aquaculture; integrated fishery projects.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Exploitation et utilisation des pêcheries ; sauvegarde des bancs de poisson ; aquaculture ; projets intégrés.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31381</code><category>313</category><name>Fishery education/training</name><name xml:lang="fr">Education et formation dans le domaine de la pêche</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31382</code><category>313</category><name>Fishery research</name><name xml:lang="fr">Recherche dans le domaine de la pêche</name><description>Pilot fish culture; marine/freshwater biological research.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Pisciculture pilote ; recherche biologique aquatique.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>31391</code><category>313</category><name>Fishery services</name><name xml:lang="fr">Services dans le domaine de la pêche</name><description>Fishing harbours; fish markets; fishery transport and cold storage.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Ports de pêche ; vente des produits de la pêche ; transport et entreposage frigorifique du poisson.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32110</code><category>321</category><name>Industrial policy &amp; admin. mgmt</name><name xml:lang="fr">Politique de l’industrie et gestion administrative</name><description>Industrial sector policy, planning and programmes; institution capacity building and advice; unspecified industrial activities; manufacturing of goods not specified below.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Politique de l’industrie, planification et programmes ; renforcement des capacités institutionnelles et conseils ; activités industrielles non spécifiées ; industries manufacturières non spécifiées ci-dessous.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32120</code><category>321</category><name>Industrial development</name><name xml:lang="fr">Développement industriel</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32130</code><category>321</category><name>Small and medium-sized enterprises (SME) development</name><name xml:lang="fr">Développement des PME</name><description>Direct support to the development of small and medium-sized enterprises in the industrial sector, including accounting, auditing and advisory services.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Soutien direct au développement des petites et moyennes entreprises dans le secteur industriel, y compris la comptabilité, l’audit et les services de conseil. </description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32140</code><category>321</category><name>Cottage industries &amp; handicraft</name><name xml:lang="fr">Artisanat</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32161</code><category>321</category><name>Agro-industries</name><name xml:lang="fr">Agro-industries</name><description>Staple food processing, dairy products, slaughter houses and equipment, meat and fish processing and preserving, oils/fats, sugar refineries, beverages/tobacco, animal feeds production.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Industries alimentaires de base, abattoirs et équipements nécessaires, industrie laitière et conserves de viande et de poisson, industries des corps gras, sucreries, production de boissons, tabac, production d’aliments pour animaux.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32162</code><category>321</category><name>Forest industries</name><name xml:lang="fr">Industries forestières</name><description>Wood production, pulp/paper production.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Industrie et travail du bois, production de papier et pâte à papier.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32163</code><category>321</category><name>Textiles - leather &amp; substitutes</name><name xml:lang="fr">Industrie textile, cuirs et produits similaires</name><description>Including knitting factories. </description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris bonneterie. </description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32172</code><category>321</category><name>Transport equipment industry</name><name xml:lang="fr">Matériel de transport</name><description>Shipbuilding, fishing boats building; railroad equipment; motor vehicles and motor passenger cars; aircraft; navigation/guidance systems.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Construction de navires, construction de bateaux de pêche ; construction de matériel ferroviaire ; véhicules automobiles et voitures particulières ; construction aéronautique ; systèmes de navigation et de guidage.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32182</code><category>321</category><name>Technological research &amp; development</name><name xml:lang="fr">Recherche et développement technologiques</name><description>Including industrial standards; quality management; metrology;  testing;  accreditation;  certification.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris les standards industriels ; gestion et contrôle de qualité ; métrologie ; accréditation ; certification.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32210</code><category>322</category><name>Mineral/mining policy &amp; admin. mgmt</name><name xml:lang="fr">Politique de l’industrie extractive et gestion administrative</name><description>Mineral and mining sector policy, planning and programmes;  mining legislation, mining cadastre, mineral resources inventory, information systems, institution capacity building and advice;  unspecified mineral resources exploitation.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Politique du secteur des industries extractives, planification et programmes ; législation et cadastre, recensement des richesses minérales, systèmes d’information ; renforcement des capacités institutionnelles et conseils ; exploitation des ressources minérales non spécifiées.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32220</code><category>322</category><name>Mineral prospection and exploration</name><name xml:lang="fr">Prospection et exploration des minerais</name><description>Geology, geophysics, geochemistry;  excluding hydrogeology (14010) and environmental geology (41010), mineral extraction and processing, infrastructure, technology, economics, safety and environment management.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Géologie, géophysique et géochimie ; à l’exclusion de hydrogéologie (14010) et géologie de l’environnement (41010), production et extraction minérales, infrastructure, technologie, économie, sécurité et gestion de l’environnement.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32261</code><category>322</category><name>Coal</name><name xml:lang="fr">Charbon</name><description>Including lignite and peat.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris lignite et la tourbe.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32262</code><category>322</category><name>Oil and gas</name><name xml:lang="fr">Pétrole et gaz</name><description>Petroleum, natural gas, condensates, liquefied petroleum gas (LPG), liquefied natural gas (LNG);  including drilling and production.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Pétrole, gaz naturel, condensés ; y compris derricks et plates-formes de forage.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32263</code><category>322</category><name>Ferrous metals</name><name xml:lang="fr">Métaux ferreux</name><description>Iron and ferro-alloy metals.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Fer et alliages.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32264</code><category>322</category><name>Non-ferrous metals</name><name xml:lang="fr">Métaux non-ferreux</name><description>Aluminium, copper, lead, nickel, tin, zinc.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Aluminium, cuivre, plomb, nickel, étain et zinc.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32265</code><category>322</category><name>Precious metals/materials</name><name xml:lang="fr">Métaux et minerais précieux</name><description>Gold, silver, platinum, diamonds, gemstones.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Or, argent, platine, diamant et pierres précieuses.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32266</code><category>322</category><name>Industrial minerals</name><name xml:lang="fr">Minerais industriels</name><description>Baryte, limestone, feldspar, kaolin, sand, gypsym, gravel, ornamental stones.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Baryte, chaux, feldspath, kaolin, sable, gypse, gravier, pierres d’ornement.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32267</code><category>322</category><name>Fertilizer minerals</name><name xml:lang="fr">Engrais minéraux</name><description>Phosphates, potash.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Phosphates, potasse.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32268</code><category>322</category><name>Off-shore minerals</name><name xml:lang="fr">Ressources des fonds marins</name><description>Polymetallic nodules, phosphorites, marine placer deposits.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Nodules métalliques, phosphorites, sédiments marins.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>32310</code><category>323</category><name>Construction policy and admin. mgmt</name><name xml:lang="fr">Politique de la construction et gestion administrative</name><description>Construction sector policy and planning; excluding construction activities within specific sectors (e.g., hospital or school construction).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Politique du secteur de la construction, planification ; ne comprend pas les activités de construction identifiables par secteur (par exemple, construction d’hôpitaux ou de bâtiments scolaires).</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>33110</code><category>331</category><name>Trade policy and admin. management</name><name xml:lang="fr">Politique commerciale et gestion administrative</name><description>Trade policy and planning; support to ministries and departments responsible for trade policy; trade-related legislation and regulatory reforms; policy analysis and implementation of multilateral trade agreements e.g. technical barriers to trade and sanitary and phytosanitary measures (TBT/SPS) except at regional level (see 33130); mainstreaming trade in national development strategies (e.g. poverty reduction strategy papers); wholesale/retail trade; unspecified trade and trade promotion activities.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Politique commerciale et planification ; soutien aux ministères et départements responsables de la politique commerciale ; législation et réformes réglementaires dans le domaine du commerce ; analyse politique et mise en œuvre des accords commerciaux multilatéraux ex. sur les obstacles techniques au commerce et les mesures sanitaires et phytosanitaires sauf au niveau régional (voir 33130) ; intégration du commerce dans les stratégies nationales de développement (ex cadres stratégiques de la lutt</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>33120</code><category>331</category><name>Trade facilitation</name><name xml:lang="fr">Facilitation du commerce</name><description>Simplification and harmonisation of international import and export procedures (e.g. customs valuation, licensing procedures, transport formalities, payments, insurance); support to customs departments; tariff reforms.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Simplification et harmonisation des procédures internationales d’importation et d’exportation (ex. évaluations de douane, procédures de licences, formalités de transport, paiements, assurances) ; soutien aux départements douaniers ; réformes tarifaires.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>33130</code><category>331</category><name>Regional trade agreements  (RTAs)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Accords Commerciaux régionaux</name><description>Support to regional trade arrangements [e.g. Southern African Development Community (SADC), Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN), Free Trade Area of the Americas (FTAA), African Caribbean Pacific/European Union (ACP/EU)], including work on technical barriers to trade and sanitary and phytosanitary measures (TBT/SPS) at regional level; elaboration of rules of origin and introduction of special and differential treatment in RTAs.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Soutien aux accords commerciaux régionaux [ex. Southern African Development Community (SADC), Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN), Zone de libre-échange des Amériques (ZLEA), Pays d’Afrique, des Caraïbes et du Pacifique/Union européenne (ACP/UE)] ; y compris le travail sur les obstacles techniques au commerce et les mesures sanitaires et phytosanitaires au niveau régional ; élaboration de règles d’origine et introduction de traitement spécial et différencié dans les accords commerciau</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>33140</code><category>331</category><name>Multilateral trade negotiations</name><name xml:lang="fr">Négociations commerciales multilatérales</name><description>Support developing countries’ effective participation in multilateral trade negotiations, including training of negotiators, assessing impacts of negotiations; accession to the World Trade Organisation (WTO) and other multilateral trade-related organisations.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Soutien à la participation effective des bénéficiaires de l’aide aux négociations commerciales multilatérales, y compris la formation de négociateurs, l’évaluation de l’impact des négociations ; accession à l’OMC et aux autres organisations multilatérales liées au commerce.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>33150</code><category>331</category><name>Trade-related adjustment</name><name xml:lang="fr">Ajustement lié au commerce</name><description>Contributions to the government budget to assist the implementation of recipients' own trade reforms and adjustments to trade policy measures by other countries; assistance to manage shortfalls in the balance of payments due to changes in the world trading environment. </description><description xml:lang="fr">Contributions au budget du gouvernement non réservées afin de soutenir la mise en œuvre des propres réformes commerciales du bénéficiaire et de ses ajustements aux politiques commerciales des autres pays ; assistance à la gestion des déficits de la balance des paiements dus au changement de l'environnement mondial du commerce. </description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>33181</code><category>331</category><name>Trade education/training</name><name xml:lang="fr">Education/formation dans le domaine du commerce</name><description>Human resources development in trade not included under any of the above codes.  Includes university programmes in trade.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Développement des ressources humaines dans le domaine du commerce non compris dans les codes ci-dessous.  Comprend les programmes universitaires dans le domaine du commerce.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>33210</code><category>332</category><name>Tourism policy and admin. management</name><name xml:lang="fr">Politique du tourisme et gestion administrative</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>41010</code><category>410</category><name>Environmental policy and admin. mgmt</name><name xml:lang="fr">Politique de l’environnement et gestion administrative</name><description>Environmental policy, laws, regulations and economic instruments; administrational institutions and practices; environmental and land use planning and decision-making procedures; seminars, meetings; miscellaneous conservation and protection measures not specified below.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Politique de l’environnement, lois et réglementations environnementales ; institutions et pratiques administratives ; planification de l’environnement et de l’utilisation des terres, procédures de décisions ; séminaires, réunions ; actions de préservation et de protection non spécifiées ci-dessous.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>41020</code><category>410</category><name>Biosphere protection</name><name xml:lang="fr">Protection de la biosphère</name><description>Air pollution control, ozone layer preservation; marine pollution control.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Lutte contre la pollution de l’air, protection de la couche d’ozone ; lutte contre la pollution marine.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>41030</code><category>410</category><name>Bio-diversity</name><name xml:lang="fr">Diversité biologique</name><description>Including natural reserves and actions in the surrounding areas; other measures to protect endangered or vulnerable species and their habitats (e.g. wetlands preservation).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris réserves naturelles et actions dans les régions environnantes ; autres mesures visant à protéger les espèces menacées dans leur habitat naturel (par exemple la protection des marécages).</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>41040</code><category>410</category><name>Site preservation</name><name xml:lang="fr">Protection des sites</name><description>Applies to unique cultural landscape; including sites/objects of historical, archeological, aesthetic, scientific or educational value.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Se rapporte à un paysage culturel exceptionnel ; y compris des sites et des objets d’une valeur historique, archéologique, esthétique, scientifique ou éducative.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>41050</code><category>410</category><name>Flood prevention/control</name><name xml:lang="fr">Prévention et lutte contre les inondations</name><description>Floods from rivers or the sea; including sea water intrusion control and sea level rise related activities.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Inondations de la mer et des rivières ; y compris la lutte contre l’avancée et la montée du niveau de l’eau de la mer.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>41081</code><category>410</category><name>Environmental education/training</name><name xml:lang="fr">Education et formation environnementales</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>41082</code><category>410</category><name>Environmental research</name><name xml:lang="fr">Recherche environnementale</name><description>Including establishment of databases, inventories/accounts of physical and natural resources; environmental profiles and impact studies if not sector specific.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris établissement de bases de données, inventaires et estimations des ressources naturelles et physiques ; profils environnementaux et études d’impact lorsque le secteur ne peut être déterminé.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>43010</code><category>430</category><name>Multisector aid</name><name xml:lang="fr">Aide plurisectorielle</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>43030</code><category>430</category><name>Urban development and management</name><name xml:lang="fr">Développement et gestion urbaine</name><description>Integrated urban development projects; local development and urban management; urban infrastructure and services; municipal finances; urban environmental management; urban development and planning; urban renewal and urban housing; land information systems.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Projets intégrés de développement urbain ; développement local et gestion urbaine ; infrastructure et services urbains ; gestion municipale ; gestion de l’environnement urbain ; planification ; rénovation urbaine, habitat ; informations sur l’occupation des sols.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>43040</code><category>430</category><name>Rural development</name><name xml:lang="fr">Développement rural</name><description>Integrated rural development projects;  e.g. regional development planning;  promotion of decentralised and multi-sectoral competence for planning, co-ordination and management;  implementation of regional development and measures (including natural reserve management);  land management;  land use planning; land settlement and resettlement activities [excluding resettlement of refugees and internally displaced persons (72010)]; functional integration of rural and urban areas;  geographical information systems.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Projets intégrés de développement rural, par exemple, planification du développement régional ; encouragement à la décentralisation des compétences plurisectorielles concernant la planification, la coordination et la gestion ; mise en œuvre du développement régional et des mesures d’accompagnement (telle que gestion des ressources naturelles) ; gestion et planification des terres ; peuplement des terres et activités de réinstallation des peuples [à l’exclusion de la réinstallation des réfugiés e</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>43050</code><category>430</category><name>Non-agricultural alternative dvpt</name><name xml:lang="fr">Développement alternatif non-agricole</name><description>Projects to reduce illicit drug cultivation through, for example, non-agricultural income opportunities, social and physical infrastructure (see code 31165 for agricultural alternative development).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Projets visant à réduire les cultures illicites (drogue) à travers, par exemple, des activités créatrices de revenu non agricoles, des infrastructures sociales et physiques (voir code 31165 pour le développement alternatif agricole).</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>43081</code><category>430</category><name>Multisector education/training</name><name xml:lang="fr">Education et formation plurisectorielles</name><description>Including scholarships.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Y compris les bourses.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>43082</code><category>430</category><name>Research/scientific institutions</name><name xml:lang="fr">Institutions scientifiques et de recherche</name><description>When sector cannot be identified.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Quand le secteur ne peut être déterminé.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>51010</code><category>510</category><name>General budget support-related aid</name><name xml:lang="fr">Soutien budgétaire</name><description>Unearmarked contributions to the government budget; support for the implementation of macroeconomic reforms (structural adjustment programmes, poverty reduction strategies); general programme assistance (when not allocable by sector).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Contributions au budget du gouvernement non réservées ; soutien à la mise en œuvre des réformes macroéconomiques (programmes d’ajustement structurel, stratégies de réduction de la pauvreté) ; y compris l’aide-programme générale (ne pouvant être ventilée par secteur).</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>52010</code><category>520</category><name>Food aid/Food security programmes</name><name xml:lang="fr">Programmes de sécurité et d’aide alimentaire</name><description>Supply of edible human food under national or international programmes including transport costs; cash payments made for food supplies; project food aid and food aid for market sales when benefiting sector not specified; excluding emergency food aid. Report as multilateral: i) food aid by the EU financed out of its budget and allocated pro rata to EU member countries; and ii) core contributions to the World Food Programme. </description><description xml:lang="fr">Fourniture nationale ou internationale de produits alimentaires y compris frais de transport ; paiements comptants pour la fourniture de produits alimentaires ; projets d’aide alimentaire et aide alimentaire destinée à la vente quand le secteur bénéficiaire ne peut être précisé ; à l’exclusion de l’aide alimentaire d’urgence.Notifier comme multilatéral : i) l'aide alimentaire consentie par l’UE et financée sur son budget propre puis répartie entre les États membres au pro rata de leur contribu</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>53030</code><category>530</category><name>Import support (capital goods)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Subventions à l’importation (biens d’équipement)</name><description>Capital goods and services; lines of credit.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Biens d’équipement et services ; lignes de crédit.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>53040</code><category>530</category><name>Import support (commodities)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Subventions à l’importation (produits)</name><description>Commodities, general goods and services, oil imports.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Produits, biens d’ordre général, importations de pétrole.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>60010</code><category>600</category><name>Action relating to debt</name><name xml:lang="fr">Action se rapportant à la dette</name><description>Actions falling outside the code headings below.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Actions non spécifiées ci-dessous.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>60020</code><category>600</category><name>Debt forgiveness</name><name xml:lang="fr">Annulation de la dette</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>60030</code><category>600</category><name>Relief of multilateral debt</name><name xml:lang="fr">Allégement de la dette multilatérale</name><description>Grants or credits to cover debt owed to multilateral financial institutions; including contributions to Heavily Indebted Poor Countries (HIPC) Trust Fund.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Dons ou prêts affectés au remboursement d’échéances dues à des institutions financières multilatérales ; y compris les contributions au fonds spécial pour les PPTE.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>60040</code><category>600</category><name>Rescheduling and refinancing</name><name xml:lang="fr">Rééchelonnement d’échéances</name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>60061</code><category>600</category><name>Debt for development swap</name><name xml:lang="fr">Echange de dette à des fins de développement</name><description>Allocation of debt claims to use for development (e.g., debt for education, debt for environment).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Affectation de créances à des fins de développement (par exemple dette pour l’éducation, dette pour l’environnement, etc.)</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>60062</code><category>600</category><name>Other debt swap</name><name xml:lang="fr">Autres échanges de dette</name><description>Where the debt swap benefits an external agent i.e. is not specifically for development purposes.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Lorsque l’échange de dette profite à un agent extérieur, i.e. n’est pas spécifiquement opéré à des fins de développement.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>60063</code><category>600</category><name>Debt buy-back</name><name xml:lang="fr">Rachat de la dette</name><description>Purchase of debt for the purpose of cancellation.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Achat de la dette en vue de son annulation.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>72010</code><category>720</category><name>Material relief assistance and services </name><name xml:lang="fr">Assistance matérielle et services d’urgence</name><description>Shelter, water, sanitation and health services, supply of medicines and other non-food relief items for the benefit of affected people and to facilitate the return to normal lives and livelihoods; assistance to refugees and  internally displaced people in developing countries other than for food (72040) or protection (72050).  </description><description xml:lang="fr">Fourniture d’abris, d’eau, d’installations sanitaires et de services de santé, de médicaments et d’autres secours non alimentaires dans le but d’aider les populations affectées et de faciliter le retour à une vie et des moyens d’existence normaux ; aide aux personnes déplacées à l’intérieur d’un pays à des fins autres qu’alimentaires (72040) ou de protection (72050).</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>72040</code><category>720</category><name>Emergency food aid</name><name xml:lang="fr">Aide alimentaire d'urgence</name><description>Food aid normally for general free distribution or special supplementary feeding programmes; short-term relief to targeted population groups affected by emergency situations.  Excludes non-emergency food security assistance programmes/food aid (52010).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Aide alimentaire pour distribution gratuite ou programmes alimentaires complémentaires ; soutien à court terme aux populations affectées par des catastrophes. Sont exclus les programmes non urgents de sécurité et d’aide alimentaire (52010).</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>72050</code><category>720</category><name>Relief co-ordination; protection and support services</name><name xml:lang="fr">Coordination des secours et services de soutien et de protection</name><description>Measures to co-ordinate delivery of humanitarian aid, including logistics and communications systems;  measures to promote and protect the safety, well-being, dignity and integrity of civilians and those no longer taking part in hostilities.  (Activities designed to protect the security of persons or property through the use or display of force are not reportable as ODA.)                                                                                                                                                </description><description xml:lang="fr">Mesures visant à coordonner l’acheminement de l’aide humanitaire, y compris les moyens logistiques et les systèmes de communication ; mesures de promotion et de protection de la sécurité, du bien-être, de la dignité et de l’intégrité des civils et des personnes qui ne prennent plus part aux hostilités. (Les activités ayant pour but de protéger la sécurité des personnes et des biens par l’usage ou la démonstration de la force ne sont pas comptabilisables dans l’APD.)</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>73010</code><category>730</category><name>Reconstruction relief and rehabilitation</name><name xml:lang="fr">Aide à la reconstruction</name><description>Short-term reconstruction work after emergency or conflict limited to restoring pre-existing infrastructure (e.g. repair or construction of roads, bridges and ports, restoration of essential facilities, such as water and sanitation, shelter, health care services); social and economic rehabilitation in the aftermath of emergencies to facilitate transition and enable populations to return to their previous livelihood or develop a new livelihood in the wake of an emergency situation (e.g. trauma counselling and treatment, employment programmes). </description><description xml:lang="fr">Travaux de reconstruction à court terme après une urgence ou un conflit limités à la remise en état des infrastructures préexistantes (par exemple, réparation ou construction de routes, de ponts ou de ports, restauration des services essentiels concernant, par exemple, l’eau et l’assainissement, les abris, les soins de santé) ; réhabilitation sociale et économique après des situations d’urgence pour faciliter la transition et permettre aux populations touchées de retrouver leurs moyens d’existen</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>74010</code><category>740</category><name>Disaster prevention and preparedness</name><name xml:lang="fr">Prévention des conflits et préparation à leur survenue</name><description>Disaster risk reduction activities (e.g. developing knowledge, natural risks cartography, legal norms for construction); early warning systems; emergency contingency stocks and contingency planning including preparations for forced displacement. </description><description xml:lang="fr">Activités visant à réduire les risques liés aux catastrophes (par exemple développement des connaissances, établissement d’une cartographie des risques naturels, de normes juridiques pour les constructions) ; systèmes d’alerte précoce, stocks d’urgence et planification d’urgence, y compris préparation à une évacuation.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>99820</code><category>998</category><name>Promotion of development awareness  (non-sector allocable)</name><name xml:lang="fr">Sensibilisation au développement</name><description>Spending in donor country for heightened awareness/interest in development co-operation (brochures, lectures, special research projects, etc.).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Dépenses dans le pays donneur afin de renforcer la sensibilisation et l’intérêt dans la coopération pour le développement (brochures, exposés, projets spéciaux de recherche, etc.).</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>15114</code><category>151</category><name>Tax policy and tax administration support</name><name xml:lang="fr">Soutien à l administration et à la politique fiscale </name><description>Support to the ministries of finance, revenue authorities or other local, regional or national public bodies on tax policy, analysis and administration (including “non-tax” public revenue).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Soutien aux ministères de finances, autorités fiscales et autres institutions publiques locales régionales et nationales sur la politique fiscale, l analyse et l administration (y compris les recettes non-fiscales.)</description></codelist-item>
</codelist-items></Codelist>
<Codelist name="SectorCategory" complete="1">
<metadata> <url>http://www.oecd.org/dac/stats/dacandcrscodelists.htm</url>
<name>"DAC 3 Digit Sector"</name></metadata>
<codelist-items>
<codelist-item><code>110</code><name>1.1 SOCIAL, EDUCATION</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>111</code><name>1.1 SOCIAL, EDUCATION</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description>The codes in this category are to be used only when level of education is unspecified or unknown (e.g. training of primary school teachers should be coded under 11220).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Les codes de cette catégorie doivent être utilisés seulement si le niveau d’éducation n’est pas spécifié ou connu (par exemple la formation d’enseignants d’écoles primaires devrait être codée sous 11220).</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>112</code><name>1.1 SOCIAL, EDUCATION</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>113</code><name>1.1 SOCIAL, EDUCATION</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>114</code><name>1.1 SOCIAL, EDUCATION</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>120</code><name>1.2 SOCIAL, HEALTH</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>121</code><name>1.2 SOCIAL, HEALTH</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>122</code><name>1.2 SOCIAL, HEALTH</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>130</code><name>1.3 SOCIAL, POPULATION</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>140</code><name>1.4 SOCIAL, WATER</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>150</code><name>1.5 SOCIAL, GOVERNMENT</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>151</code><name>1.5 SOCIAL, GOVERNMENT</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description>N.B. Use code 51010 for general budget support. </description><description xml:lang="fr">N.B. Utiliser le code 51010 pour le soutien budgétaire général.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>152</code><name>1.5 SOCIAL, CONFLICT</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description>N.B. Further notes on ODA eligibility (and exclusions) of conflict, peace and security related activities are given in paragraphs 76-81 of the Directives.</description><description xml:lang="fr">N.B.  Des notes supplémentaires sur l’éligibilité au titre de l’APD (et les exclusions) des activités liées aux conflits, la paix et la sécurité sont données dans les paragraphes 76-81 des Directives.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>160</code><name>1.6 SOCIAL, OTHER</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>210</code><name>2.1 ECO, TRANSPORT</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description>Note: Manufacturing of transport equipment should be included under code 32172.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Nota bene : La fabrication de matériel de transport devrait être incluse dans le code 32172.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>220</code><name>2.2 ECO, COMMUNICATION</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>230</code><name>2.3 ECO, ENERGY</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>240</code><name>2.4 ECO, BANK</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>250</code><name>2.5 ECO, BUSINESS</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>311</code><name>3.1 PROD, AGRICULTURE</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>312</code><name>3.2 PROD, FORESTRY</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>313</code><name>3.3 PROD, FISHING</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>321</code><name>3.4 PROD, INDUSTRY</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>322</code><name>3.5 PROD, MINING</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>323</code><name>3.6 PROD, CONSTRUCTION</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>331</code><name>3.7 PROD, TRADE</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>332</code><name>3.7 PROD, TRADE</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>410</code><name>4.1 MULTISECTOR, ENVIRONMENT</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description>Covers activities concerned with conservation, protection or amelioration of the physical environment without sector allocation.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Secteur non spécifié.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>430</code><name>4.3 MULTISECTOR, OTHER</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>510</code><name>5.1 NON SECTOR, PROGRAMME AID</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description>Budget support in the form of sector-wide approaches (SWAps) should be included in the respective sectors. </description><description xml:lang="fr">Les soutiens budgétaires sous la forme d’approches sectorielles devraient être inclus dans les secteurs respectifs.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>520</code><name>5.3 NON SECTOR, FOOD</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>530</code><name>5.1 NON SECTOR, PROGRAMME AID</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description>Non-food commodity assistance (when benefiting sector not specified).</description><description xml:lang="fr">Aide sous forme de produits non alimentaires (quand le secteur bénéficiaire ne peut être précisé).</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>600</code><name>5.2 NON SECTOR, DEBT</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>700</code><name>5.4 NON SECTOR, EMERGENCY</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description>Within the overall definition of ODA, humanitarian aid is assistance designed to save lives, alleviate suffering and maintain and protect human dignity during and in the aftermath of emergencies.  To be classified as humanitarian, aid should be consistent with the humanitarian principles of humanity, impartiality, neutrality and independence.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Selon la définition générale de l’APD, l’aide humanitaire est destinée à sauver des vies, à atténuer les souffrances, et à préserver et protéger la dignité humaine pendant et après des situations d’urgence. Pour être comptabilisée dans l’aide humanitaire, les apports d’aide doivent être conformes aux principes humanitaires d’humanité, d’impartialité, de neutralité et d’indépendance.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>720</code><name>5.4 NON SECTOR, EMERGENCY</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description>An emergency is a situation which results from man made crises and/or natural disasters.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Une situation d’urgence a pour origine une crise provoquée par des actions humaines ou par une catastrophe naturelle.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>730</code><name>5.4 NON SECTOR, EMERGENCY</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description>This relates to activities during and in the aftermath of an emergency situation.  Longer-term activities to improve the level of infrastructure or social services should be reported under the relevant economic and social sector codes. See also guideline on distinguishing humanitarian from sector-allocable aid. </description><description xml:lang="fr">Activités menées pendant et après une situation d’urgence. Les activités à plus long terme destinées à améliorer le niveau d’infrastructure ou de services sociaux doivent être rapportées sous les codes correspondants des secteurs économiques et sociaux pertinents. Voir également les orientations sur la distinction entre l’aide humanitaire et l’aide ventilable par secteur.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>740</code><name>5.4 NON SECTOR, EMERGENCY</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description>See codes 41050 and 15220 for prevention of floods and conflicts.</description><description xml:lang="fr">Voir codes 41050 et 15220 pour la prévention des inondations et des conflits.</description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>910</code><name>5.5 NON SECTOR, OTHER</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>930</code><name>5.5 NON SECTOR, OTHER</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description></description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
<codelist-item><code>998</code><name>5.5 NON SECTOR, OTHER</name><name xml:lang="fr"></name><description>Contributions to general development of the recipient should be included under programme assistance (51010).</description><description xml:lang="fr"></description></codelist-item>
</codelist-items>
</Codelist>
</CodeLists>
